<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The practical rule of Christian piety containing the summ of the whole duty of a true disciple of Christ. Written originally in Latin by Benedictus Aria Montanus, and translated into English by A. Lovel, M.A.</title>
            <author>Arias Montano, Benito, 1527-1598.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 224 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 142 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25801</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3679A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R214868</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826924</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826924</idno>
            <idno type="VID">31335</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25801)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 31335)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1881:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The practical rule of Christian piety containing the summ of the whole duty of a true disciple of Christ. Written originally in Latin by Benedictus Aria Montanus, and translated into English by A. Lovel, M.A.</title>
                  <author>Arias Montano, Benito, 1527-1598.</author>
                  <author>Lovell, Archibald.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 244 [i.e. 276] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Joseph Hindmarsh, bookseller to his Royal Highness, at the Black Bull in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by Archibald Lovell, of the Latin original by Benito Arias Montano.</note>
                  <note>Final page misnumbered 244.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian ethics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:31335:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31335:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PRACTICAL RULE OF Chriſtian Piety: CONTAINING The Summ of the <hi>whole Duty</hi> of a true Diſciple of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Written Originally in Latin By <hi>Benedictus Aria Montanus,</hi> AND Tranſlated into Engliſh By <hi>A. LOVEL,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Joſeph Hindmarſh,</hi> Bookſeller to his Royal Highneſs, at the <hi>Black Bull</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:31335:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31335:2"/>
            <head>THE Author's Preface TO THE Chriſtian READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THEY who from the Study of the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of worldly things, learn and do confeſs that God takes care of ſublunary affairs; do clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceive that the rough Tempeſt wherein moſt Chriſtian People are at preſent toſſed, is not the effect of the uncertain influences of the Stars, nor that it is raiſed by hidden and obſcure cauſes. None of them doubt, but that the publick Calamities of
<pb facs="tcp:31335:3"/> Kingdoms, People and Cities, are ſent by the Judgment and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God the avenger of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs; and that before they happen, they are Propheſied and foretold by Pious and Choſen Men, for the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of divine Juſtice, and the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of the lives of ſinful Men; as it is written:</hi> Amos 3. Can two walk together, except they be agreed? Will a Lion roar in the Forreſt when he hath no Prey? will a young Lion cry out of his Den, if he have taken nothing? Can a Bird fall in a ſnare upon the Earth, where no Gin is for him? Shall one take up a Snare from the Earth, and have taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all? Shall a Trumpet be blown in the City, and the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple not be afraid? Shall there be evil in a City, and the Lord hath not done it? Surely the Lord God
<pb facs="tcp:31335:3"/> will do nothing, but he revealeth his ſecret unto his ſervants the Prophets. <hi>Now for what cauſes ſuch Commotions are raiſed both in publick and private affairs, the ſame Prophet does declare:</hi> pubiſh in the Palaces at <hi>Aſhdod,</hi> and in the Palaces in the Land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and ſay, aſſemble your ſelves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Mountains of <hi>Samaria:</hi> and behold the great tumults in the midſt thereof, for they know not to do right, ſaith the Lord, who ſtore up Violence and Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery in their Palaces. Therefore thus ſaith the Lord, an adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry there ſhall be even round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Land; and he ſhall bring down thy ſtrength from thee, and thy Palaces ſhall be ſpoiled.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To me, truly, the viſible cauſe o' the divine Judgment againſt us
<pb facs="tcp:31335:4"/> appears to be our publick and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſins; whilſt I ſee the greateſt part of Chriſtians rent into ſeveral Sects, not only ſeduced and led a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by many errors, but alſo proud and puffed up in them; and others who live in the Communion of the Church, and profeſs the true Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, neglecting the duties of the ſame, and almoſt wholly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting it: and ſo, whilſt I reflect upon the depraved minds of ſome, and the corrupt and diſſolute lives of others, and the Diſſentions, Jars, Oppoſitions, Enmities and perverſe courſes of both, I often think with my ſelf upon this.</hi> The Lord looked down from Heaven, upon the Children of Men; to ſee if there were any that did under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and ſeek God. They are all gone aſide, they are altogether become filthy: there is none that doth good, no not one.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:31335:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Tho I neither be a Prophet, nor the Son of a Prophet, yet I dare be bold to foretel greater Storms hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over our heads, unleſs they be prevented: It is enough to me, to make me affirm this; that I ſee thoſe crimes in the Earth, which God Almighty by infallible Oracles has threatned not to let go unpuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. For if the Lion roar, who will not be afraid? if the Lord hath ſpoken, who ſhall not prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie? Therefore he may very lawfully predict future evils, who ſees the manifeſt cauſes, from which, God Almighty, calling Heaven and Earth to witneſs, has foretold that diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult and ſad times will ariſe.</hi> Iſa. 1. <hi>Now the cauſes which I obſerve, I think are obvious to all Men, to wit,</hi> Deut. 32. <hi>our contumacy and inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, our hardned obſtinacy in wicked
<pb facs="tcp:31335:5"/> courſes; and a kind of contending with God that puniſhes us; which the Prophet</hi> Iſaiah <hi>takes notice of in the Jews. Iſai.</hi> 1. Why ſhould ye be ſtricken any more? ye will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt more and more: The whole head is ſick, and the whole heart faint. From the ſole of the foot even unto the head, there is no ſoundneſs in it; but wounds, and bruiſes, and putrifying ſores: they have not been cloſed, neither bound up, neither mollified with Ointment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And, would to God! that in this toſſing and agitation of the World there were no other loſs but of the wealth, dignities, ſplendour and honours of the age, which tho they be highly valued, yet it might juſtly be born with, nay and perhaps to be wiſhed, ſeeing ſuch heavy loads and burdens are many times
<pb facs="tcp:31335:5"/> hinderance to the proſperity of our courſe: but, which is moſt ſad and grievous, when the danger of the loſs of one poor ſoul ought, in right, to be prevented by the throwing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-board of all the goods and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go of the Ship; yet in ſuch doleful Ship-wrecks, innumerable numbers of ſouls are obſerved to periſh, and be ſwallowed up in the deep; which is the greateſt of all humane miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Now ſeeing it is the duty and office of the Maſters and Pilots, to beſtir themſelves for the ſafety of the beaten Veſſel; and that I obſerve many of thoſe who are concerned, diligently labouring for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; tho I want both authority and skill to act amongſt thoſe who rule the Ship; yet as being of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe, who in common dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ought not to be idle ſpectators but buſie in lending a hand, or at
<pb facs="tcp:31335:6"/> leaſt aſſiſtant with fervent prayers, I thought it my duty, according to the mean and low ſtation that I ſtand in, in the Church of God, with all humility and modeſty to propoſe what I have judged proper for remedying of the evils, whereof the cauſes are ſo obvious to be known; eſpecially ſince we bend our care to the admoniſhing and help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thoſe, who when they are unable to underſtand higher and greater matters, are not, perhaps, frequently taught thoſe things which are more uſeful, and neceſſary to be known of all Men in general; and which if they be ignorant of, they can never attain to ſalvation, nor to the knowledge of thoſe Points which are reckoned more noble and ſublime truths. Nor do we fear that theſe our endeavours will ſeem un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable or ſuperfluous to thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:31335:6"/> great Men, who are more learned and skilful in the art of inſtructing and teaching the way of living; we are rather confident that the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate will approve of our deſign, hoping that if we have given any hints that may ſerve for foreward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their duty, they will take it kindly and in good part. For in great Storms, the chief Maſters and Pilots, receive ſometimes good advice from the Paſſengers, when they are pleaſed to hear them. In how much then, we have learned from the Doctrine and Word of God, for the obtaining of God the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our ſouls in the next World, and publick Peace and Tranquillity in this, we conceive two things are to be done, the one is, that we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere in the pure and holy Faith of the Catholick Church; and the other that we endeavour the amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:31335:7"/> of our lives and manners, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Rules and Precepts of our Lord and Maſter, conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly praying againſt ſin that endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers our ſouls, and for eternal life, which is their happineſs and bliſs. If theſe things be purely, religiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and holily ſet about, they will procure us the grace and mercy of God through Jeſus Chriſt; as the Holy Ghoſt by the mouth of his Prophet does aſſure us: Pſal.</hi> 107. Oh that Men would praiſe the Lord for his goodneſs, and for his wonderful works to the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Men. They that go down to the Sea in Ships, that do bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs in great waters: Theſe ſee the works of the Lord, and his wonders in the deep. For he commandeth and raiſeth the ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my Wind, which lifteth up the waves thereof. They mount up
<pb facs="tcp:31335:7"/> to the Heaven, they go down a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to the depths, their ſoul is melted becauſe of trouble. They reel to and fro, and ſtagger like a drunken Man, and are at their wits end. Then they cry unto the Lord in their trouble, and he bringeth them out of their diſtreſſes. He maketh the Storm a Calm, ſo that the waves thereof are ſtill. Then are they glad becauſe they be quiet; ſo he bringeth them unto their deſired haven. Oh that Men would praiſe the Lord for his goodneſs, and for his wonderful works to the Chilren of Men. Let them exalt him alſo in the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the People, and praiſe him in the Aſſembly of the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:31335:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Whoſe is wiſe, and will obſerve theſe things, even they ſhall under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the loving kindneſs of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:31335:8"/>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>THE Practical Rule OF Chriſtian PIETY.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Firſt Part.</head>
               <p>THE ſcope and deſign of all Philoſophers, who have treated of the Nature and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Man, and have given pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and rules for the conduct of humane life, ſeems to have been to find out and demonſtrate a ſupreme Perfection, to which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:31335:9"/> when Man had once attained, he had no further deſires to diſturb him, but reſted content in an entire and peaceable enjoyment of the chief and moſt<note place="margin">Humane Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city.</note> deſirable good: And this they called a ſtate of Happineſs or Bliſs. Conſtant and daily experience made it manifeſt, that<note place="margin">The common condition of life.</note> the way of living, which moſt part of Mankind followed, being obnox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ious to care and anxiety, labour and pain, trouble and perturba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoughts, came far ſhort of that perfection of humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that reſt and tranquillity of mind that Mankind aſpired to: And that the various ſtates and conditions of Men, made no difference in the caſe; ſeeing Kings, Princes, Magiſtrates, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:31335:9"/> common People, the Rich and the Poor, the Whole and the Sick, all were diſſatisfied and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie in their own condition. Wherefore many have made it their buſineſs to ſearch out and diſcover ſeveral means, how they might attain to that chief good, which might produce a ſolid and univerſal repoſe in the minds of all Men. But the different biaſs of paſſions and inclination ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided and diſtracted the thoughts of the undertakers, that they were wide of the Mark, and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the way of finding true happineſs: for ſome placed <hi>chief good,</hi> in the delights and pleaſures of the Body; others in the afflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Riches; others again in <hi>indolence</hi> or exemption from grief and pain; and ſome in a freedom from all Paſſions and Affections:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:31335:10"/> Every one in their ſeveral Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and Actions, purſued the end they had propoſed to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and laid down Maxims and Rules for others to do the like, whom by large promiſes and exhortations, they invited to the ſame courſe of life.</p>
               <p>However the Opinion of thoſe who placed the chief end and happineſs of Man in bodily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, pleaſures and ſenſual luſts, in the judgment of the wiſer, hath been totally exploded; As not only in the act and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of delights and pleaſure; but alſo in the manner of attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them, rendering the nature of Man inferiour and more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy than that of Beaſts.</p>
               <p>But the opinion of thoſe who made the perfection of life chiefly to conſiſt in the ſoundneſs of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:31335:10"/> mind, and in virtue; tho in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral it was approved; yet the determination of the things that did conſtitute, and the method preſcribed for arriving at that fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity, were found liable to ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny errors and difficulties, that being meaſured by, and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the ſtandard of true hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, they were at length con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and rejected as ineffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual. For ſome being ignorant of the true Original of the Souls of Men, and not acknowledging God for the author of them; they fancied to themſelves a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain perfection of Virtue, which they were ſo far from attaining to, that neither they, nor their Diſciples could ever reach within the view thereof. Some again, tho they knew God to be the Supreme and true. Author of Humane
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:31335:11"/> Nature, yet they owned him not to be the chief end and happineſs of Man; and tho, indeed, they might acknowledge that, yet without the revealed will of God himſelf, they could not rightly underſtand how they ought to ſeek, and by what means come to the enjoyment of him; nay and that alſo being known, they could not without the aſſiſtance of divine Grace, ſet about the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the duties required therein. God was, therefore, in the firſt place, to be known and applied to by Faith, and that ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Maſter to be conſulted, who might ſhew and declare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his Doctrine unto them, by thoſe ſecret and divine ways whereby he can, and is wont to do it: <hi>for without Faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God.</hi> But the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:31335:11"/> quite contrary courſe was taken by thoſe, who attributed ſo much to the induſtry and ſharpneſs of humane underſtanding that they thought that there was nothing to be ſought from God, judging it unſeeming a quaint and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curate Philoſopher, to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the will of God, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the act rather of a ſlothful Soul, than of a prying and inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Mind, that ſearched into the nature of things. That Man might and ought of himſelf find out the excellent nature of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, carefully and induſtriouſly purſue after, and labour to obtain it, and having obtained it, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and improve the ſame: which tho they promiſed to themſelves, and endeavoured to accompliſh; yet ſeeing they were neither rooted in Faith, nor had
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:31335:12"/> begged and deſired the aid of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Grace; their ſearch was in vain, ſo that no where finding what they lookt for; they fatal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſled themſelves and thoſe that followed them: And loſing all hopes of attaining to the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs they propoſed, they at length degenerated into the baſeſt and moſt corrupt kind of life. This the Holy Ghoſt takes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, and thus condemns, <hi>Eph. 4. This I ſay therefore and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie in the Lord, that ye hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth walk not as other Gentiles walk in the vanity of their mind, having the underſtanding darkned, being alienated from the life of God, through the ignorance that is in them, becauſe of the blindneſs of their heart, who being paſt feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, have given themſelves over un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to laſciviouſneſs to work all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:31335:12"/> with greedineſs.</hi> They again who were not without a ſenſe and knowledge of God, but would not conform to a ſteddy and ſure rule of Conduct, ſtudying rather to follow their own humour, than to comply with the ſimplicity of truth, have broached moſt idle Notions of the excellence of the divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and erroneous and moſt dangerous Perſwaſions of the way of imitating the ſame; lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moſt part of Mankind firſt into error and a ſnare, and then into utter deſtruction; as it is written: <hi>Rom. 1. The wrath of God is revealed from Heaven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all ungodlineſs and unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of men, who hold the truth in unrighteouſneſs, becauſe that which may be known of God, is manifeſt in them; for God hath
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:31335:13"/> ſhewed it unto them. For the invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible things of him from the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World are clearly ſeen, being underſtood by the things that are made, even the Eternal Power and Godhead; ſo that they are without excuſe. Becauſe that when they knew God, they glorified him not as God, neither were thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but became vain in their imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and their fooliſh heart was darkned, Profeſſing themſelves to be wiſe, they became fools: and changed the glory of the uncorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble God, into an image made like to corruptible Man, and to Birds and four-footed Beaſts, and creep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things. Wherefore God alſo gave them up to uncleanneſs, through the luſts of their own hearts, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonour their own bodies between themſelves: who changed the truth of God into a lie, and worſhipped
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:31335:13"/> and ſerved the creature more than the Creator, who is bleſſed for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi> The Doctrine therefore of Men that had no conformity to the Faith of God, or that fell off from the knowledge of God, unto Vanity, falſe and fooliſh ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, could neither rightly define, nor exhibit and declare the true happineſs of Mankind. That only Doctrine which the revealed Will of God doth teach, is capable through the power and goodneſs of its author, to perform what it hath promiſed to thoſe who truly and ſincerely become its Diſciples. For the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Pſal. 119. The Proud have digged Pits for me, which are not after thy Law. All thy Commandments are Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:31335:14"/>
               <p>There are many inſtances which manifeſtly prove, that the Doctine of the word of God hath fulfilled and made good what it promiſed and foretold to the true Diſciples and followers thereof; and that it can and dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly does perform the ſame, to thoſe who are guided thereby. Now this Doctrine hath promiſed Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, eternal happineſs and the inheritance of the kingdom of Heaven, in and through the Son of God, who was to be ſent into the World, and the deſcent of the Holy Ghoſt into the minds of Believers, which as a ſure pledge and earneſt of the celeſtial inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, might by his inſpirations teach them the true and ſaving uſe of the Heavenly gifts and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; of this the Diſciples of our Lord had experience, as the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:31335:14"/> Ghoſt himſelf bears witneſs. 2 <hi>Pet. 1. Simon Peter, a Servant and an Apoſtle of Jeſus Chriſt to them that have obtained the like precious Faith with us, through the righteouſneſs of God, and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt: Grace and Peace be multiplied unto you through the knowledge of God, and of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus our Lord, according as his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Power hath given unto us all things that pertain unto life and godlineſs, through the knowledge of him that hath called us to glory and virtue: whereby are given unto us exceeding great and precious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; that by theſe you might be partakers of the divine nature, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving eſcaped the corruption that is in the World through luſt.</hi> The Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> treating of the vanity of the Doctrine of the Gentiles, and of the truth and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:31335:15"/> of the Chriſtian Diſcipline, ſays to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Eph. 4. But ye have not ſo learned Chriſt; if ſo be that ye have heard him, and have been taught by him, as the truth is in Jeſus: That ye put off concerning the former converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the old man, which is corrupt according to the deceiful luſts: And be renewed in the ſpirit of your mind; and that ye put on the new man, which after God is created in righteouſneſs, and true holineſs.</hi> Acts 3. <hi>Ye are the Children of the Prophets, and of the Covenant which God made with our Fathers, ſaying unto Abraham, and in thy Seed ſhall all the kindreds of the earth be bleſſed. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto you firſt God having raiſed up his Son Jeſus, ſent him to bleſs you, in turning away every one of you from his iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:31335:15"/>
               <p>Now that ſtate and condition to which the true Diſciples and Followers of the Chriſtian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine are by the grace and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God advanced, does in honor, dignity, and amplitude of glory and bliſs far exceed all that the natural Man, the Wit of Philoſophers, and the pains and ſtudy of mortal Man can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, define or comprehend, without the ſpecial favour and aſſiſtance of divine grace: <hi>Iſa. 64. For, eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, neither have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the heart of man, the things which God hath prepared for them that love him.</hi> 1 Cor. 2. <hi>But God hath revealed them unto us by his Spirit, for the Spirit ſearcheth all things, yea, the deep things of God. For what Man knows the things of a Man, ſave the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:31335:16"/> ſpirit of Man that is in him? even ſo the things of God knoweth no Man, but the ſpirit of God.</hi> This ſtate and condition may in ſome meaſure, indeed, be delineated and deſcribed, which by the help of God, in time and place conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent we ſhall attempt: but that will be but a faint emblem and adumbration, rather than a true and lively repreſentation of the ſame; for the fulneſs of this ſolid and excellent happineſs, is not to be expreſſed in the common way of ſpeech, nor conceived by the thoughts of men, unleſs of thoſe who by the influence and operation of the Holy Ghoſt, are rendred capable of ſo great myſteries. <hi>Eph. 3. For this cauſe, ſaith the Apoſtle, I bow my knees to the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, of whom the whole Family
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:31335:16"/> in Heaven and Earth is named, that he would grant you according to the riches of his glory, to be ſtrengthened with might, by his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the inner man; that Chriſt may dwell in your hearts by Faith; that ye being rooted and grounded in love, may be able to comprehend with all Saints, what is the breadth, and length, and depth, and height; and to know the love of Chriſt, which paſſeth knowledge, that ye might be filled with all the fulneſs of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, although a Diſciple of this Chriſtian Doctrine may not at firſt, comprehend the greatneſs and excellence of the ſtate to which he is called, until by divine favour he hath attained to it; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs the dignity and extent of the happineſs is not therefore leſs, nor will it by any diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:31335:17"/> be diminiſhed; for the moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> faithful Author of this Doctrin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will abundantly and to the ful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> perform what he hath promiſed tho in the beginning it be un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>known to believers, ſeeing h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> who freely and graciouſly hath promiſed, ſtandeth not in need o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the goodneſs of others, nor i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> made poorer by conferring hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> own; but by how much the mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he is liberal and bountiful, by ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> much the riches of his goodneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and inexhauſtible mercy does en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>creaſe: <hi>Rom. 10. For the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Lord over all, is rich unto all tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> call upon him.</hi> Whether, then<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the reward of the Diſcipline of Chriſt, be fully known to his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, or but darkly ſhadowed out to them; yet it ſhall not be denied to thoſe who with a pure and holy heart ſeek after it, nor
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:31335:17"/> ſhall it want any thing of that amplitude and fulneſs, which the divine nature of the thing it ſelf, and the Majeſty, Authority and Bounty of him that promiſes it, does require. <hi>Eſa. 55. For as the Heavens are higher than the Earth, ſo are my ways higher than your ways, and my thoughts than your thoughts. For as the rain com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth down, and the ſnow from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and returneth not thither, but watereth the Earth, and maketh it bring forth and bud, that it may give ſeed to the ſower, and bread to the eater: ſo ſhall my word be that goeth forth of my mouth: it ſhall not return unto me void, but it ſhall accompliſh that which I pleaſe, and it ſhall proſper in the thing whereto I ſent it, for ye ſhall go out with joy, and be led forth with peace: the Mountains and the Hills ſhall
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:31335:18"/> break forth before you into ſinging and all the trees of the field ſhe clap their hands. Inſtead of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Thorn ſhall come up the Fig-tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and inſtead of the Bryar ſhall com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> up the Myrtle tree: and it ſhe be to the Lord for a name, for a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> everlaſting ſign that ſhall not b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cut off.</hi> A clear proof of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> appears in <hi>Abraham,</hi> whom God heretofore, having ſelected and ſeparated him from the Doctrin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Manners of the Gentiles, pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſed as an excellent pattern to be imitated by thoſe who would imbrace and ſubmit to this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline; how he having received and by firm Faith believed th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> promiſe of an earthly inheritance did not inſtantly know what ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tent of Land was aſſured to him referring that to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Almighty who had made the Promiſe: but
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:31335:18"/> thought it was enough for him to relie on the promiſes of the God of the whole Earth, who having freely ſpoken the word, was beſt able; and moſt willing to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it. And no ſooner was the Promiſe made, but he truſting it, obeyed the command and ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the conditions enjoyned him: <hi>Gen. 12. For the Lord ſaid unto Abraham, get thee out of thy Country, and from thy kindred, and from thy Fathers houſe, unto a Land that I will ſhew thee, and I will make of thee a great Nation, and I will bleſs thee, and make thy Name great; and thou ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be a bleſſing. And I will bleſs them that bleſs thee; and curſe him that curſeth thee: and in thee ſhall all families of the Earth be bleſſed.</hi> So <hi>Abraham</hi> departed, as the Lord had commanded him, knowing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:31335:19"/> neither whither he went, nor how large the poſſeſſion was, that he was to have: which the Apoſtle obſerving, ſaith: <hi>By Faith Abra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ham when he was call'd to go out into a place which he ſhould after receive for an inheritance, obeyed; and he went out not knowing whither he went:</hi> wholly truſting to the word of him who could and would perform more than he was able either to ask or think<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and looking upon it as his duty to obey the Maſter whoſe Diſciple he was, that had promiſed him large inheritance, to be revealed and diſcovered unto him in due time, as the event made appear<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For <hi>Abraham</hi> having made a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent progreſs in the diſcipline he had embraced, being called by God to whoſe inſtitution he had reſigned himſelf, was fully inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:31335:19"/> by him, not only in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent of the Earthly inheritance, but of the Heavenly Bleſſings al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, which were ſhadowed and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pified thereby; as it is written: <hi>Gen. 13. And the Lord ſaid unto Abraham, after that Lot was ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from him, lift up now thine eyes, and look from the Place where thou art, North-ward, and South-ward, and Eaſt-ward, and Weſt-ward. For all the Land which thou ſeeſt, to thee will I give it, and to thy Seed for ever. And I will make thy Seed as the duſt of the Earth: ſo that if a Man can number the duſt of the Earth, then ſhall thy Seed alſo be numbred. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, walk through the Land, in the length of it, and in the breadth of it: for I will give it unto thee.</hi> Wherefore ſeeing no Man can doubt but that what things God
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:31335:20"/> hath promiſed, will more fully be accompliſhed, than he who is to receive them can wiſh for, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> think; it will be the duty of a true Believer and Diſciple of Chriſt, to ſet diligently about the performance of the condition impoſed upon him, and to leave the bleſſings and favours which he does expect to the arbitrement of him, to whoſe conduct and doctrine he hath reſigned himſelf even to God Almighty the powerful and rich Father of all Mercies, who maketh it to rain upon the Juſt and the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, and who by the mouth of his own Son, in whom he hath ſpoken and made the greateſt of promiſes to us, hath promiſed to give his good ſpirit to thoſe that ſeek him. For if he moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly fulfilled what at ſundry
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:31335:20"/> times and in divers manners he ſpake and promiſed unto the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by the Prophets; and if the word ſpoken by Angels was ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt, how can we be denied or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed of any thing that hath been promiſed to us by the Son of his Love; the faithful interpreter of his Will, and bountiful diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of his Grace and Mercies. This made a moſt approved Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, who by his own and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of others was convinced of that truth, break out in thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to God: <hi>Rom. 8. What ſhall we then ſay to theſe things? If God be for us who can be againſt us? He that ſpared not his own Son, but delivered him up for us all, how ſhall he not alſo with him freely give us all things?</hi> So that on the part of him that promiſes no doubt can be made nor any impediment
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:31335:21"/> interpoſe, why thoſe things which have been promiſed, ſhould not ſuperabundantly be fulfilled: <hi>Luke 6. good meaſure, preſſed down, and ſhaken together, and running over, ſhall men give into your boſom.</hi> And the truth of this Chriſtian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine for ever ſtands firm and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaken, <hi>Tit. 1. According to the Faith of Gods Elect, and the acknowledging of the truth, which is after godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: In hope of eternal life, which God who cannot lie, promiſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the World began; but hath in due times manifeſted his word.</hi> Heb. 6. <hi>For when God made promiſe to Abraham, becauſe he could ſwear by no greater, he ſware by himſelf, ſaying, ſurely, bleſſing, I will bleſs thee, and multiplying, I will multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply thee. And ſo after he had pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently endured, he obtained the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. For Men verily ſwear by the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:31335:21"/> greater: and an Oath for confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation is to them an end of all ſtrife. Wherein God willing more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly to ſhew unto the Heirs of Promiſe the immutability of his counſel, confirmed it by an Oath: that by two immutable things, in which it was impoſſible for God to lie, we might have a ſtrong conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who have fled for refuge to lay hold upon the hope ſet before us: which hope we have as an anchor of the Soul, both ſure and ſtedfaſt, and which entereth into that within the Vail, whither the forerunner is for us entered, even Jeſus, made an High Prieſt for ever after the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Melchiſedec.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It remains then, which is the deſign of this little Book, that we handle the Parts and Offices that are incumbent on Believers and the Scholars of Chriſt, but
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:31335:22"/> eſpecially thoſe which indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concern all ranks, ages, and conditions of Men, and without which their learning will be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in vain, and the Doctine inſignificant. Let every one then, whether King or Prieſt, Prince or States-man, private or publick, rich or poor, Bond or Free, Father or Son, Husband or Wife, Young or Old, Merchant or Artificer, Soldier or Peaſant, Learned or Unlearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, provided he profeſs himſelf to be a Diſciple and Follower of Chriſt and Chriſtian Doctrine, provided he be Baptized into the Faith of the Catholick Church, without which there is no Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; let every one, I ſay, learn in what Station ſoever he be, how he ought to keep his Poſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have and carry himſelf in this World, and that from the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:31335:22"/> and Inſtitutions of the Holy Ghoſt himſelf, who ought to be his Guide, and not from us, who do but, as Students in the ſame School, deliver to our fellow Scholars the Precepts and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of our great Maſter who hath called us from Darkneſs to his marvellous Light, and let him take it in good part, if perchance we inculcate ſome things which way ſeem hard and uneaſie to the Manners, Cuſtoms and Opinions of this preſent Age, not interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting what we ſay as a reproof to any perſon in particular; but judging it the duty of a faithful Miniſter and Servant, to declare and manifeſt to his fellow ſervants the Will of the Lord in his own words; whereby if any Man out of Conſcience, Ignorance or Fear ſhal think himſelf cenſured, he muſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:31335:23"/> not be offended with the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Precepts which are Juſt and Holy, nor with his fellow Servant who delivers them, but with himſelf, his faults and vices, who having profeſſed this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, hath not ſubmitted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the Laws and Conditions thereof, which are Conſtant, U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal and Immutable, and not made and publiſhed, that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the deſire, humour, luſt and counſels of every private man, they may be altered and changed; but which command Obedience by changing all thoſe Deſires, Paſſions, Luſts, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels that may be a hindrance to the punctual obſervation of the ſame, our Lord himſelf having ſaid, <hi>Mat. 5. Think not that I am come to deſtroy the Law or the Prophets: I am not come to deſtroy
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:31335:23"/> but to fulfill.</hi> That is, to make thoſe who believe in me, pure, holy, and faithful in obſerving and fulfilling the ſame. <hi>For verily I ſay unto you, till Heaven and Earth paſs, one jot or tittle ſhall in no wiſe paſs from the Law, till all be fulfilled. Whoſoever therefore ſhall break one of theſe leaſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and ſhall teach Men ſo, he ſhall be called the leaſt in the Kingdom of Heaven: but whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall do and teach them, the ſame ſhall be called great in the Kingdom of Heaven. For I ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, that except your righteouſneſs ſhall exceed the righteouſneſs of the Scribes and Phariſees, ye ſhall in no caſe enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> Now if the entry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kingdom of Heaven be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to thoſe, whoſe righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and obedience to the Laws
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:31335:24"/> of God, does not exceed that of the Scribes and Phariſees, not of the wicked and hypocrites, but of the good Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, who ſeemed moſt to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell in the ſtudy of obſerving the Law: what will become of him, who through hatred, or favour of Man, ſhall pervert, change, conceal, diſſemble, or any other ways make void the rules of righteouſneſs that he is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver to his fellow Chriſtians, and teach ſo? He ſhall, indeed, be called the leaſt in the Kingdom of Heaven, and deemed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to be admitted into that Heavenly Communion and Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, into which all that are recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, are called Kings and great. Now, to be a King, and to be the leaſt are inconſiſtent; hence it follows that in the Kingdom of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:31335:24"/> Heaven, it is the ſame thing to be the leaſt, and to be none; for no man that breaketh the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God and teacheth others ſo to do<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhall enter into the Kingdom of Heaven; but they only ſhall enter, whoſe righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs <hi>exceeds the righteouſneſs of the Scribes and Phariſees,</hi> and who being <hi>not only hearers, but doers of the Law, ſhall be juſtified before God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore if in the Precepts, Rules, and Inſtructions of the Doctrine that hath been deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto us, any thing may ſeem to any Man ſtricter than his own Will, Opinion, or predominant Affections can comply with, or ſubmit unto, let him, if he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to enter into life, be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded, that neither the way which God hath once fenced in,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:31335:25"/> is to be changed or enlarged, nor that ſtrait and narrow Gate made wider, for the ſake of any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Perſon; and that he muſt become Humble, Lowly, and poor in Spirit, ſtriving to walk in the narrow way, and to enter at the ſtrait Gate, which will not be difficult to thoſe who truly love this Doctrine, and earneſtly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore the aſſiſtance of Divine Grace, that will be denied to none who dutifully and carefully ſubmit to the rules and dictates of this Diſcipline. For, <hi>Pſal. 145. The Lord is nigh unto all them that call upon him, to all that call upon him in truth. He will fulfill the deſire of them that fear him: he alſo will hear their cry, and will ſave them.</hi> And ſo he ſhall underderſtand that the ways of the Lord are broad and pleaſant
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:31335:25"/> to thoſe who as Pilgrims and Strangers abſtaining from, and renouncing the carnal deſires that war againſt the Soul, and becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poor in Spirit, undertake that holy Journey and enter into the right way; as the Royal Pſalmiſt ſaith. <hi>Pſal. 119. And I will walk at liberty: for I ſeek thy Precepts. I will ſpeak of thy Teſtimonies alſo before Kings, and will not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. And I will delight my ſelf in thy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Commandments which I have loved. My hands alſo will I lift up unto thy Commandments which I have loved: and I will meditate in thy Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know that good and holy Men will willingly liſten to their fellow Chriſtian, and not ſo much mind the language and learning of him that writes, as the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings which proceed out of the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:31335:26"/> mouth of the living God, whoſe ſacred and infallible Authority reaching all men, whether pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick or private, the Univerſal Church hath always owned and aſſerted, and that they will take in good part, whatſoever may be ſaid by us which perhaps may tax the corrupt manners of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent times; being perſwaded that Chriſtian Simplicity, Virtue and Probity are always in force, and beyond exception and reproach, not only upon their own account, but becauſe of our purpoſe and deſign alſo, who heartily love all holy and good Men tho unknown, neither hate any who may have fallen from the truth, or degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the Virtues of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, but wiſh that all may repent and be ſaved through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, whom therefore
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:31335:26"/> we would have rightly admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of their Duty. As for the wiſer, who ſtand not in need of our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, we truſt, they will put a favourable conſtruction on our care and endeavours for the common ſalvation of Mankind; who tho we be ſimple, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to contribute any thing to the information of the wiſe, yet to thoſe who are weaker in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg ought to perform what ſervice and good offices lye in our power. Now the ſum of all our Admonition ſhall conſiſt of plain Sentences from the Oracles both of the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the weight of which is ſuch, that neither humane wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom can reſiſt, nor the craft and ſubtilty of our adverſary evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the force of them; and by this means we may be helpful
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:31335:27"/> both to thoſe who admit of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in diſpute, but what is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from holy Scripture, and to thoſe alſo who rightly think, that truth wherever it be found, ought to be embraced: for to both theſe it is our deſign to do good, not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging all that might be ſaid, but only ſuch things as we ſhall have reaſon to think may be profitable to all, and hurtful to no body.</p>
               <p>The whole Chriſtian Diſcipline then may be comprehended under two general Heads, which every true Diſciple and follower of Chriſt, ought to know and duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully practiſe. The firſt is, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Word and Promiſes of God, the Authority whereof hath been confirmed by Signs, Miracles and manifeſt Teſtimonies. Now Signs and Miracles are neither at preſent neceſſary, nor are they, nor
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:31335:27"/> indeed ought to be required; as being of old ſeen and approved, reiterated likewiſe, and confirmed, and received and believed by the Univerſal Church of God: for concerning theſe, it is written, <hi>Deut. 32. Remember the days of old, conſider the years of many Generations: ask thy Father and he will ſhew thee, thy Elders, and they will tell thee.</hi> Wherefore it is not now to be doubted, what it is, or how we ought to believe; for that is reduced into certain Points, which are called Articles, and propoſed by the Church to be learned, under the name of the Apoſtles Creed, briefly and plainly comprehending all the Points of our Faith, which have been largely commented upon and explained, in the many wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of holy and learned Men.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:31335:28"/> Neither is our diſcourſe directed to thoſe that do not believe, but to ſuch as believe, or at leaſt, profeſs they believe the Word and Promiſes of God to their own Salvation, and confeſs that there is no neceſſity of Miracles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor any doubt of the Salvation ſent into the World, and wrought by Jeſus Chriſt; <hi>Heb. 2. Which at firſt began to be ſpoken by the Lord, and was confirmed unto us by thoſe that heard him; God alſo hearing them witneſs, both with Signs and Wonders, and with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Miracles, and gifts of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, according to his own Will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond Head and Branch of Doctrine is, the knowledg and practice of Piety, of which at preſent we are to treat. Now, for illuſtration ſake, we call Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:31335:28"/> all that which every faithful Diſciple and Follower of Chriſt and the Chriſtian Doctrine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving the Promiſes, ought to know, hold faſt, and practiſe, no Man being excepted who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the right uſe of his Reaſon, can know and perform the ſame, ſeeing the aſſiſtance of the divine Grace that is neceſſary to that knowledg and practice, will not be wanting nor denied to thoſe who, as we ſaid before, diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſeaſonably beg the ſame, but will rather be plentifully ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied by the Father of Light, 1 <hi>Tim. 2. who will have all men to be ſaved, and to come unto the knowledg of the Truth;</hi> even thoſe who are ſtrangers to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the Truth, and much more ſuch as embrace the known Truth, and ſtudy to hold faſt and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:31335:29"/> it. Now we ſay, that it behoveth a Diſciple of Chriſt, to know the chief Precepts and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of the Doctrine of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which he profeſſes: for tho to know the leaſt Points be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the duty, nor is it required of all; yet thoſe things which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to all in general, and every Diſciple in particular, are not to be unknown. For how dare he profeſs and call himſelf a Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who knows not the Heads of that Diſcipline which he does and ought to follow? And by what right can he expect to be acknowledged a Scholar by the Maſter, who knows not the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and Inſtitutions of his Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er? And to that purpoſe is this, which by a Diſciple is written to his fellow Scholars: 1 <hi>Cor. 14. If any Man think himſelf to be a
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:31335:29"/> Prophet, or Spiritual, let him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg that the things that I write unto you, are the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord. But if any Man be ignorant, let him be ignorant.</hi> If any Man know not the Commands of God, he ſhall not be known by our Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, who will ſay, <hi>Mat. 25. I know you not.</hi> And again, <hi>to every one that hath ſhall be given: but from him that hath not ſhall be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, even that which he hath.</hi> In another place making a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt thoſe who believe and know the Will of God, and thoſe who do not, the Lord ſaith, <hi>Luke 12. And that Servant which knew his Lords Will, and prepared not himſelf, neither did according to his Will, ſhall be beaten with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtripes; but he that knew not, and did commit things worthy of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:31335:30"/> ſtripes, ſhall be beaten with few ſtripes.</hi> Wherefore leaving thoſe who know not the Will of the Lord, ſuch as are they to whom the knowledg of the Goſpel hath not as yet reached; our diſcourſe is to thoſe, who have known, or at leaſt have profeſſed to know the Will of the Lord, who ought to prepare themſelves and do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Will; to whom the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Theſ. 4. For ye know what commandments we gave you by the Lord Jeſus. For this is the Will of God, even your Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> to which Men ought to prepare themſelves. Now, no Man can be ſo prepared, if he be ignorant by what means and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that Preparation is to be ſet about and accompliſhed: for tho one may ſet about it with all ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable care and ſtudy, yet unleſs
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:31335:30"/> he ſquare the ſame according to the rules and and directions of the Divine Will, he will at length find it to be unprofitable. And this God Almighty himſelf plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares to thoſe, who moved with a pious ſtudy and zeal, yet propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to themſelves other courſes, than were enjoyned them by his Counſel and Precepts. <hi>Iſa. 48. Thus ſaith the Lord thy Redeemer, the Holy One of Iſrael, I am the Lord thy God which teacheth thee to profit, which leadeth thee by the way that thou ſhouldſt go. Oh that thou hadſt hearkned to my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments: then had thy Peace been as a River, and thy Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as the Waves of the Sea.</hi> From which holy Sentences, it follows, that every Diſciple ought at leaſt to know the chief Heads of the Diſcipline that is profitable unto
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:31335:31"/> him; thoſe, I mean, which may be known, retained and practiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by all, and require neither muc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Labour, great Study, a deep Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> length of Time, nor far Trav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> for attaining to the knowledge them; as it is written, <hi>Deut. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> For this Commandment which I com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mand thee this day, is not hidd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> from thee, neither is it far off. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> is not in Heaven that thou ſhould ſay, who ſhall go up for us to He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ven, and bring it unto us, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> may hear it, and do it? Neither it beyond the Sea, that thou ſhould ſay, who ſhall go over the Sea for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> and bring it unto us, that we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> hear it and do it? But the Word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> very nigh unto thee, in thy mout<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and in thy heart, that thou ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> do it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Piety then, that is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> known and practiſed by us, is d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:31335:31"/> into three parts: to wit, <hi>Fear, Repentance,</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> with the obſervation of the Laws of God; which whoſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rightly taught, ſhall keep and obſerve, they will through the moſt bountiful Promiſe and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of God, confirm and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe to him the Grace and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Lord, to his own Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and at length bring him to the poſſeſſion and enjoyment of the Kingdom of Heaven. For ſuch is the efficacy that the Will and bounteous Liberality of God hath granted to theſe three Parts, or Virtues, if you had rather call them ſo, that he whoſe mind is fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and endowed with them, may thereby avoid the wrath and dreadful Judgment of God, and find Grace and Mercy in the Eyes of the Almighty.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:31335:32"/>
               <p>In the firſt place then, they who would practiſe the Duties of Chriſtian Piety, muſt have their minds filled with a divine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Fear: that is, with an awe, reverence, and watchful obſervation of thoſe things, which are known to be either acceptable or diſpleaſing to God, that they may wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, flie and abhor the laſt, and with all care and diligence pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue and ſeek after the firſt. For that diſpoſition, whereby the mind ſo reverences God, that it wills no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which may offend that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence goodneſs, and rejects no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which it knows to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to the Will of God; that diſpoſition of mind, I ſay, is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the fear of the Lord, and is ſaid to be the beginning of all true Wiſdom, which by another name alſo the Latins have called Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:31335:32"/> Philoſophers have divided this into a ſervile and filial fear, and the Chriſtian School have admitted the ſame diſtinction, condemning the ſervile fear ſo far, as it was a forerunner to, and made way for the filial. But we, whoſe deſign it is not ſo much to diſpute nicely about theſe matters, as to accommodate them to vulgar ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities, and to ſquare our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe according to the rule of ſacred Oracles, following the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition given by the Holy Ghoſt, call this fear of the Lord, Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion or Reverence, whereby the mind of an holy Man being affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, obſerves and follows what he knows to be acceptable to God: and on the contrary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects and ſhuns what is diſpleaſing to him. Wherefore this pious diſpoſition of mind is by Wiſdom
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:31335:33"/> ſo defined: <hi>The fear of the Lord is the beginning</hi> (or principal part) <hi>of Wiſdom,</hi> that is to ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a Religious obſervation of thoſe things which by Knowledg or Wiſdom, we know to be deſired or ſhunned. Now by Wiſdom in this place, is to be underſtood the knowledg and notices o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the divine Will, whether attained by word, writing, or tradition or by revealed rules and rational intimations.</p>
               <p>Now this divine Fear puts him in whoſe heart it is, upon the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of true repentance, incline him to the Study and obſervation of the Laws of God, and ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him up to a ſearch and dili<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gent enquiry into the nature o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> both. For when once a Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath reſolved with himſelf t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reverence and practiſe all tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:31335:33"/> he knows to be acceptable to God, and to flie and ſhun thoſe things which do diſpleaſe him; he makes it his chief care to learn what it is that God approves of, and what he condemns; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo taught, he implores the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of the divine Grace, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents of the former ſins of his miſpent life, and propoſes to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the way of Gods Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, wherein perſiſting in a ſteddy and uninterrupted courſe, he is made partaker of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Promiſes ſtipulated by the Covenant of Grace, and enjoys the fellowſhip and communion of that bleſſing, which the Father of Love has promiſed, can, and will make good to them who believe in him, and which, in effect, he hath fulfilled to thoſe who have obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his moſt Juſt and Holy Will.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:31335:34"/>
               <p>Wherefore the Wiſdom of God knowing what extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fruits ſpring from this root of divine fear; that it might dehort Men from the violation of the Laws of God, and deter them form the danger of everlaſting Wrath and indignation; by the mouth of the Son of <hi>Sirach;</hi> call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ecclus. 1. The fear of the Lord, a Crown of Wiſdom, Honour, and Glory, and Gladneſs, and a Crown of Rejoycing.</hi> And to explain and commend it more effectually and plainly, ſaith, <hi>that the fear of the Lord is a Fountain of Life.</hi> The fear of God is therefore called the beginning and fountain of Life, becauſe reclaiming Man from the violation of the Laws of God, and inducing him to true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, it ſets him upon the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and performance of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:31335:34"/> that he may obtain Grace and Mercy in the ſight of the Almighty, whereby he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the ſon of God and heir of eternal Life, through the moſt gracious Promiſe and Covenant of that God, who freely and of his own accord takes upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the care, conduct, inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſanctification of all thoſe who cleave unto him by Faith and true Obedience; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Royal Pſalmiſt ſings: <hi>Pſal. 145. He will fulfil the deſire of them that fear him: he alſo will hear their cry, and will ſave them:</hi> and in another place, Pſal. 103. <hi>For as the Heaven is high above the Earth: ſo great is his Mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them that fear him. As far as the Eaſt is from the Weſt, ſo far hath he removed our tranſgreſſions from us, Like as a Father pitieth
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:31335:35"/> his Children: ſo the Lord pitieth them that fear him.</hi> And again. <hi>The Mercy of the Lord is from everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to everlaſting upon them that fear him.</hi> By all which, we are taught that the never failing Mercy of God is infinite &amp; eternal to thoſe who filled and animated with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Fear, follow the ways of Godlineſs: which Fear, as we have ſaid, is the beginning, or principal part of Knowledg, that is, it is a reverent care to avoid ſin, obey the Will, and worſhip the Majeſty of God. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the holy Mother of our Lord affirms: <hi>Luke 1. That his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is on them that fear him, from Generation to Generation;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by intimating, that that divine and inexhauſtible Mercy was in no Age ever wanting to thoſe who Fear and religiouſly Serve
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:31335:35"/> the Lord. And, indeed, divine Wiſdom hath by many and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Teſtimonies and Oracles out of the mouths of all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Holy Men, aſſerted the Dignity and Excellence of the Fear of God; and amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by that of the Son of <hi>Sirach:</hi> Ecclus. 25. <hi>Oh how great is he that findeth Wiſdom! yet there is none above him that feareth the Lord.</hi> For Knowledg and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom do, indeed, illuminate and inſtruct the Mind; but that holy Fear of the Lord turns the heart effectually unto God, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines it to the Obedience and Obſervation of the Precepts of the divine Law. As the ſame Son of <hi>Sirach</hi> does expreſly teach, <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 2. ſaying, <hi>My Son, if thou come to ſerve the Lord, prepare thy Soul for Temptation. Set thy Heart
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:31335:36"/> aright, and conſtantly endure, and make not haſt in time of trouble. Cleave unto him, and depart not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, that thou maiſt be encreaſed at thy laſt end. Whatſoever is brought unto thee take chearfully, and be patient when thou art chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to a low eſtate. For Gold is tried in the Fire, and acceptable Men in the Furnace of Adverſity. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in him, and he will help thee; order thy way aright and truſt in him. Ye that fear the Lord, wait for his Mercy, and go not aſide, leſt ye fall. Ye that fear the Lord, believe him, and your reward ſhall not fail. Ye that fear the Lord, hope for good, and for everlaſting Joy and Mercy. Look at the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations of old, and ſee: did ever any truſt in the Lord, and was confounded? Or did any abide in his fear, and was forſaken?, Or,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:31335:36"/> whom did he ever deſpiſe, that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon him? For the Lord is full of Compaſſion and Mercy, Long-Suffering, and very Pitiful, and forgiveth Sins, and ſaveth in time of Affliction. Wo be to fearful hearts, and faint hands, and the ſinner that goeth two ways. Wo unto him that is faint-hearted, for he belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not, therefore ſhall he not be defended. Wo unto you that have loſt Patience: and what will ye do when the Lord ſhall viſit you? They that fear the Lord, will not diſobey his Word, and they that love him, will keep his ways. They that fear the Lord, will ſeek that is well pleaſing unto him, and they that love him ſhall be filled with the Law. They that fear the Lord will prepare their heart, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble their Souls in his ſight, ſaying, we will fall into the hands of the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:31335:37"/> Lord, and not into the hands of men: for as his Majeſty is ſo is his Mercy.</hi> Nor do the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures affirm only that the Fear of God is an uſeful, proper and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual means for working out our own Salvation; but alſo that it is abſolutely neceſſary, and without which no Man can be ſaved; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he who is not endowed with this Religious and Godly Fear, can neither rightly ſet about, nor with a ſteddy and conſtant purpoſe of mind, go through with the work of Repentance; nor yet faithfully keep the Laws of God, as they ought to do, who endeavour to approve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to God, and procure the bleſſing of Juſtification and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Sanctification. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was the Decree and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of Heaven that a meſſenger
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:31335:37"/> of the Salvation which was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the World, ſhould as a fore-runner be ſent before, to Preach the Repentance and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Divine Laws to Men, and by that means prepare the way for Chriſtian Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. <hi>Mat. 3. For John the Baptiſt came preaching in the Wilderneſs of Judea, and ſaying, Repent ye: For the Kingdom of Heaven is at hand. For this is he that was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of by the Prophet Eſaias, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The voice of one crying in the Wilderneſs, prepare ye the way of the Lord, make his paths ſtreight.</hi> For the ſame purpoſe the Apoſtles were ſent out by Jeſus Chriſt the Author and High-Prieſt of our Salvation, to Publiſh and Preach this neceſſary Duty of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: for, as the Evangeliſt ſaith, <hi>Mark 6. They went out and Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:31335:38"/> that Men ſhould Repent.</hi> The Apoſtles excepted none that heard them, and deſired to be partakers of the Salvation which they Preached, from the Duty and Care of Repentance. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> affirms before King <hi>Agrippa,</hi> that he was enjoyned and had performed the ſame duty, both towards the Jews and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, without any diſtinction: <hi>Preaching throughout all the waſts of Judea, and then to the Gentiles, that they ſhould repent, and turn of God, and do works meet for repentance.</hi> When the Jews and others at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> asked the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, what was to be done by thoſe who deſired to be ſaved, St. <hi>Peter</hi> anſwered: <hi>Acts 2. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and be Baptized every one of you in the name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, for the remiſſion of Sins,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:31335:38"/> and ye ſhall receive the gift of the Holy Ghoſt. For the Promiſe is unto you, and to your children, and to all that are afar off, even as many as the Lord our God ſhall call.</hi> It might be proved by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ſix hundred Teſtimonies from the Holy Scripture, that without the fear of the Lord and Repentance, which is the ſecond Head of Doctrine we now treat of, and without the keeping and obſervation of the Laws of God, no Man that is come to Age, and that knows God and the nature of good and evil, can obtain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins, and the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and enjoyment of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven. This, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour himſelf, the beſt Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his Fathers will aſſerts, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Luke 13. Except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh: Mat.</hi> 5.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:31335:39"/> 
                  <hi>and except your righteouſneſs ſhall exceed the righteouſneſs of the Scribes and Phariſees, ye ſhall in no caſe enter into the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> Now ſeeing the word <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> is often to be mentioned in this little Book, that it may clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear what we mean, we are to take notice that Repentance comprehends two things; a dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation and forſaking of our ſins and ill life paſt, and an earneſt and ſincere practice and performance of thoſe Virtues, Acts, and Deeds which are known to be accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God. As to the firſt part, that is, the deteſtation and forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of ſin and a ſinful life; that Repentance chiefly relates to it, which is enjoyned and taught by the Chriſtian Church; of which the particulars are, the ſorrow and contrition of heart, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:31335:39"/> of the mouth, and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in deed; to uſe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon phraſe and expreſſion of the learned: for knowing the nature whereof, we ſhall refer you to the Books of the Learned who have fully handled and diſcuſſed that Point; being reſolved here only to treat of the Virtue and Grace of Repentance, which is the end and complement of that other part: for it is not enough to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and bewail what is paſt, as is commonly ſaid, to confeſs our ſins, and not commit the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; unleſs they who can, do bring forth fruits worthy of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. And therefore this part, which conſiſts in the amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life, and in the exerciſe and practice of Righteouſneſs, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe called the Virtue and Grace of Repentance, is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:31335:40"/> whereof we ſhall treat at preſent.</p>
               <p>Now the Doctrine of the Holy Scriptures makes this <hi>Repentance</hi> the Grace of Heavenly Wiſdom, to conſiſt chiefly in this; That Man ſhould war againſt his own Luſts, ſubdue and overcome his natural affections, abſtain from worldly and carnal works, and with all care and induſtry endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to perform what is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded and approved of by God. For this Law was laid upon the firſt Parent of Mankind, by that Myſterious and Divine Oracle, delivered under the Name and Figure of the Earth, <hi>Gen. 3. Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is the Earth for thy ſake; in Sorrow ſhalt thou eat of it all the days of thy life. Thorns alſo and Thiſtles ſhall it bring forth to thee: and thou ſhalt eat the herb of the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:31335:40"/> field. In the ſweat of thy face ſhalt thou eat bread.</hi> God declared to Man that that humane Earth cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Adam,</hi> from whence he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf had the name of <hi>Adam,</hi> was for his ſake, that is, for his tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of the Command of God, curſed and made diſobedient, foretelling him, that in ſorrow and labour he ſhould eat of the fruits of that earth, which was not, through the curſe become al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together ſo barren, that it would bring forth no good fruit, but that the good and profitable fruit which it did bring forth, muſt be the effect of much labour and pain. For as that Earth was of it ſelf, to bring forth nothing but Thorns and Thiſtles, that is, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious difficulties ſpringing from Luſt and Pride, which muſt be rooted out by him who deſires to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:31335:41"/> feed on good and generous fruit; ſo there is need of indefatigable pains and labour, even to the ſweat of the brow, that is, to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering and diſciplining the Will and Affections, that by ſo doing he may obtain that heavenly bread which God hath promiſed, fully to beſtow upon thoſe, who in that manner work out their own Salvation. Many Oracles of divine Scripture confirm the truth of this; as, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. &amp; 3. <hi>To him that overcometh and keepeth my works to the end, will I give to eat of the Tree of Life which is in the midſt of the Paradiſe of God, and a Crown of Life. And I alſo will give him to eat of the hidden Manna; and will give him a white ſtone, and in the Stone a new Name written, which no Man knoweth, ſaving he that receiveth it. And I will give him
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:31335:41"/> the Morning Star, and he ſhall be cloathed in white Robes, and I will not blot out his name out of the Book of Life; but will make him a Pillar in the Temple of my God, and he ſhall go no more out: and I will write upon him the name of my God, and the name of the City of my God, which is the new Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, and my new name.</hi> Rev. 21. <hi>He that overcometh ſhall inherit all things, and I will be his God, and he ſhall be my Son. But the fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and unbelieving, and the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable, and Murderers, and Whoremongers, and Sorcerers, and Idolaters, and all Liars ſhall have their part in the Lake wich burneth with Fire and Brimſtone, which is the ſecond death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The gracious goodneſs of God to admoniſh us of theſe things, and of what concerns our Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:31335:42"/> gives to all and every ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner this ſeaſonable warning <hi>Rev. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I counſel thee to buy of me gold tried in the fire, that thou mayeſt be rich and white raiment that thou mayeſt be cloathed, and that the ſhame of thy nakedneſs do not appear; be zealous therefore and repent. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I ſtand at the door and knock: if any man hear my voice, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the door, I will come in to him, and will ſup with him, and he with me.</hi> Moſt graciouſly and freely then, does the Lord invite to the joys of his Supper, all who being decently cloathed and prepared as they ought, pray and long for the gladneſs of that moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Feaſt, which being liberally offered by him that invites them, they ſhall at length fully enjoy, and rejoyce with him who hath made them partakers of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:31335:42"/> Promiſes. But we have a clear Inſtance, that he who durſt come to the Wedding-Feaſt, not cloathed with the Wedding Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is, Repentance and the obſervation of the Precepts of Chriſt, was rebuked by the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry King, and had this dreadful check and ſentence: <hi>Mat. 22. Friend, how cameſt thou in hither, not having the Wedding Garment? Then ſaid the King to his Servants, bind him hand and foot, and take him away, and caſt him into outer darkneſs: there ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi> The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, therefore, of the Goſpel requires not only Faith, but Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience alſo, in him who deſires to be an Heir of the promiſed Salvation: and this Obedience be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins by a true and unfeigned Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and ſhews it ſelf in the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:31335:43"/> ſerious exerciſe thereof; heavy Judgments being denounced by God upon thoſe who obey no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Law of the Goſpel. No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by the Goſpel Law, in this place we mean, the conditions requ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red of them, who really and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> effect deſire to be made partaker<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of theſe glad tidings; for other<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe without Repentance and the obſervation of the Precepts of God, Men are ſo far from ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the divine Promiſes, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they muſt certainly expect the wrath and anger of God; 2 <hi>They 1. In flaming Fire, taking Veng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ance of them that know not God and that obey not the Goſpel of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall be p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhed with everlaſting deſtruction from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glory of his power; wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he ſhall come to be glorified in b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:31335:43"/> Saints, and to be admired of all them that believe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now this Wedding-Garment, which every one that is called to the Marriage, and deſires to be admitted into that holy Feaſt, muſt and ought to be cloathed with, is made up of Repentance, and the obſervation of the divine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts; and that it is ſo, we have the word of the King himſelf, the Lord and Maſter of the Feaſt for it, who commanded his Servants whom he ſent to call the Gueſts, Saying: <hi>Mat. 22. Go ye there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and teach all Nations, Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing them in the name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt; teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoever I command you:</hi> That is to ſay, Repentance, and the ſtudy and obſervation of the Precepts and Commands of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:31335:44"/> God; For ſo the Lord himſelf expounds it, who, when he went about performing the office of an Evangeliſt, taught publickly, <hi>Mark</hi> 1. ſaying: <hi>The time is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, and the Kingdom of God is at hand: Repent ye and believe the Goſpel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A clear inſtance of this is to be ſeen in <hi>Abraham,</hi> whom God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed as a pattern of his free and moſt gracious Election, exhibiting unto us under the type and figure of earthly and ſenſual things the whole and ſum of this great my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery: for ſuch was the counſel of God, that what things really and truly happened unto him, the ſame ſhould ſhadow out and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the ſpiritual bleſſings which belonged to us. As it is written; 1 <hi>Cor. 10. All theſe things happened unto them for enſamples,</hi>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:31335:44"/> (<hi>or types) and they are written for our admonition, upon whom the ends of the World are come. Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> being firſt called, believed in God who had called him, and promiſed to make him a Father of many Nations; In God I ſay, who calleth thoſe things which be not as tho they were: and truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the divine election, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that to be the moſt accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble obedience to God, when one willingly and diligently complies with his call, and without doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> undergoes that ſaving diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, as proceeding from him; who being the Fountain of all Goodneſs, freely beſtows himſelf, His Graces and Bleſſings, upon thoſe who believe and obey him: ſo that when he was commanded by him, from whom he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Promiſe, to leave his Country, his Kindred, and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:31335:45"/> Houſe; he obeyed, and went out, leaving thoſe advantages, which thoſe who live after the manner of this world, reap from their Country, Kindred, and Fathers Houſe; for the native Country affordeth acquaintance and confidence, the Fathers Houſe, Wealth and Riches, and Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, Means and Subſtance to thoſe who lead their lives according to the dictates of Luſt and Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Abraham,</hi> therefore, depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as the Lord had commanded him, leaving his Country, Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and Fathers Houſe, and choſe to be a Stranger and Sojour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in a ſtrange Land, following the Command of God that called him. Now we know, that Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Sojourners have no mind, means, nor confidence, to ſpend their time in delights, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, ſo long as they think of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:31335:45"/> their condition, and behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves like Strangers and Sojour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and propoſe to themſelves, that that is not their Country or place of reſt, but an Inn or place of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment, which they muſt ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly leave, and go forward unto a place of more commodious habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. So <hi>Abraham</hi> being called and commanded to go out of his Country, into a Land that was to be ſhewn to him, not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, but obeyed and put it in execution: for he really and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed forſook his Country, Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and Fathers Houſe, and not in word and inclination alone. He ſaid not, I will do it, or I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to do it, and did it not; but actually performed what he was commanded: and in that manner <hi>Abraham believed in God, and it was accounted to him for Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; not that he believed only,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:31335:46"/> but that believing he obeyed, and went out unto a place which he was to receive for an inheritance, not knowing whither he went. Heb. 11. And that by Faith he Sojourned in the Land of Promiſe, as in a ſtrange Countrey, dwelling in Tabernacles, with Iſaac and Jacob, the Heirs with him of the ſame Promiſe.</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this precedent, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is called to the gifts and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of the Heavenly Promiſes, believes in, and would pleaſe him that hath promiſed, deſiring to have them made good unto him, muſt not only by Faith, Will, and Inclination, but alſo in Deed and in good Earneſt, renounce the Pomp, Vanity, Corruption, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, Pleaſures, Ambition and other Vices of this World, and perform what he obliged himſelf to and promiſed, before the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:31335:46"/> Trinity, (in which he profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his belief,) in preſence of his God-Fathers, God-Mothers and Witneſſes in his Baptiſm, through the grace and aſſiſtance of him that called him, to whoſe ſervice he reſigned himſelf, and in whoſe name he was Baptiſed, that is, in the name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, which grace and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance will never be wanting to thoſe, who from a pure and holy heart implore and beg the ſame, as we have already demonſtrated: <hi>Luke 12. I am come to ſend fire on the Earth, and what will I if it be already kindled?</hi> Now he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to renounce the Devil and all his Works, the Pomps and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of this wicked World: and what are the works of the Devil, and Vanities of the World, but Ambition, Luſt, Avarice, and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:31335:47"/> the delights and pleaſures of the Fleſh? that is to ſay, the corrupt manners &amp; cuſtoms of this World, which, according to the Doctrine of the Apoſtles, breed, cheriſh and encreaſe ſin and wickedneſs, as it is written: 1 <hi>John 2. Love not the World, neither the things that are in the World. If any Man love the World, the love of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is not in him. For all that is in the World, the Luſt of the Fleſh, the Luſt of the Eyes, and the Pride of Life, is not of the Father, but is of the World.</hi> And again, the Apoſtle S. <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>James 4. Ye Actulterers and Adultereſſes, know ye not that the friendſhip of this World is enmity with God? Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever therefore will be a friend of the World, is the enemy of God. Do ye think that the Scripture ſaith in vain, The Spirit that dwelleth in
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:31335:47"/> us, luſteth to envie?</hi> Wherefore we muſt not only by Faith and in words, but in our endeavours, acts, and deeds renounce all worldly Pleaſures, Luſts and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition; for Virtue conſiſts not in words, but in deeds. And therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Tim. 2. If a Man therefore purge himſelf from theſe, he ſhall be a veſſel unto honour, ſanctified and meet for the Maſters uſe, and prepared unto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very good work.</hi> And St. <hi>Peter</hi> alluding to <hi>Abraham</hi> thus admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth: 1 <hi>Pet. 2. Dearly belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, I beſeech you, as Strangers, and Pilgrims, abſtain from fleſhly Luſts, which war againſt the Soul, having your Converſation honeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Gentiles, that whereas they ſpeak againſt you as evil doers, they may by your good works which they ſhall behold, glorifie God in
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:31335:48"/> the day of Viſitation.</hi> Wherefore that Faith which is commended and praiſed in <hi>Abraham,</hi> was not an idle and dead, but a living Faith, quickned by Charity, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſelf in the practice and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Obedience, and ſo it was imputed to him for Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, becauſe he really left his Country, Kindred, and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe, and obediently went unto the place appointed him; thereby ſetting before us a lively inſtance of true Obedience. Which <hi>Moſes</hi> imitating, <hi>Heh. 11. when he was come to years, refuſed to be called the Child of</hi> Pharaohs <hi>daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, chuſing rather to ſuffer afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the People of God, than to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon: eſteeming the Reproach of Chriſt greater Riches than the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in Egypt: for he had a reſpect
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:31335:48"/> unto the recompence of Reward. By Faith he forſook Egypt, not fearing the wrath of the King: for he endured as ſeeing him who is inviſible.</hi> In deeds then and not in words alone, or an empty and idle boaſting of Faith, muſt eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one ſhew himſelf obedient to God, and bring forth the fruits of ſerious Repentance; as in his holy Baptiſm he promiſed. But how is that performed by thoſe, who never depart from iniquity? or if they do, it is but for a time, upon occaſion of Confeſſing, or taking the Sacrament, that they may again fall into the ſame or more heinous crimes, when not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the conditions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of a Penitent that would worthily receive the Sacrament, are ſatisfaction and amendment of life; which, if ſometime they ſet about it, they ſoon forſake, and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:31335:49"/> relapſe into the accurſed manners of a ſtubborn &amp; inflexible nature, but not he that beginneth, <hi>Mat. 24 but he that ſhall endure unto the end, the ſame ſhall be ſaved.</hi> Iſa. 1. <hi>Waſh ye, make you clean, put away the evil of your doings from before mine eyes: ceaſe to do evil, learn to do well, ſeek Judgment, relieve the oppreſſed, Judge the fatherleſs, plead for the widow. Come now and let us reaſon together ſaith the Lord: though your ſins be as Scarlet, they ſhall be as white as Snow, tho they be red like Crimſon, they ſhall be as Wooll. Ceaſe to do evil, learn to do well,</hi> ſaith God, who comparing the noble beginnings of Chriſtian ſimplicity and Piety, with the ſubſequent corruption of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and defect of Repentance and Obedience in his ancient Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, thus laments over them:
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:31335:49"/> 
                  <hi>How is the faithful City become an Harlot? It was full of Judgment: Righteouſneſs lodged in it, but now Murderers. Thy Silver is become droſs, thy Wine mixt with Water. Thy Princes are rebellious, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions of Thieves are every one that loveth Gifts, and followeth after Rewards: they judge not the Fatherleſs, neither doth the cauſe of the Widow come unto them.</hi> That Faith then which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with Repentance and Obedience, is the Faith whereby Men obtain the gracious promiſes of God: not, I ſay, an idle and dead Faith, but that which work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by Charity, and believes and obeys the word of God, does what is commanded, and is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred by no difficulties, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with heroick reſolution and aſſurance performs whatever is
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:31335:50"/> enjoyned it: as it is written. <hi>Heb. 11. By Faith they paſſed through the Red Sea, as by dry Land: which the Egyptians eſſaying to do were drowned. By Faith the Walls of Jerico fell down, after they were compaſſed about ſeven days. By Faith the Harlot</hi> Rahab <hi>periſhed not with them that believed not: when ſhe had received the Spies with Peace. And what ſhall I now ſay? For the time would fail me to tell of</hi> Gideon <hi>and of Baruch, and of</hi> Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pſon, <hi>and of</hi> Jeptha, <hi>of</hi> David <hi>and alſo</hi> Samuel, <hi>and of the Prophets: who through Faith ſubdued King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, wrought Righteouſneſs, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained Promiſes, ſtopped the mouths of Lions, quenched the violence of the Fire: eſcaped the edg of the Sword, out of weakneſs were made ſtrong, waxed valiant in Fight, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to flight the Armies of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liens.
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:31335:50"/> Women received their dead, raiſed to life again.</hi> So that the Faith of all thoſe ſhewed it ſelf in great Works, it being their care and ſtudy to approve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to God not barely by the profeſſion of an idle Faith, but by the obedience and practice of a lively and active Faith, and to omit nothing that for Godlineſs ſake they were commanded to do, and on the contrary, to act no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, which Religion and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience taught them to ſhun and avoid, and rather to ſuffer all inconveniencies and loſſes, even to death and reproach, than to vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late thoſe Precepts, which the will and word of God delivered to be obſerved by them. And therefore they alſo, have left to Poſterity patterns and examples of true Repentance, and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:31335:51"/> as it follows in the ſame place: <hi>And others were tortured, not accepting deliverance, that they might obtain a better reſurrection. Others had trials of cruel mockings and ſcourgings; yea, moreover of Bonds and Impriſonment. They were ſtoned, they were ſawn aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, were ſlain with the Sword, they wandred about in Sheep-skins, and Goat-skins, being deſtitute, afflicted, tormented: of whom the World was not worthy: they wandred in Deſarts, and in Mountains, and in Dens and Caves of the Earth. And theſe all having obtained a good report through Faith, received not the Promiſe: God having provided ſome better thing for us: that they without us ſhould not be made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</hi> The Apoſtle calls the works of thoſe holy Men, and their practice of Obedience, the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:31335:51"/> of Faith, as well in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoing and acting what they were commanded to act and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo, as in declining and ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thoſe things that were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited to be done; and yet they obtained not the Promiſe, that is, not the full enjoyment of the Kingdom of Heaven, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Death and Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt was not as yet opened; that they might not be made perfect without us, who came at the eleventh hour, tho they were ſeverally at ſeveral hours before us, bore the heat and burden of the day, and wrought diligently in the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. However, muſt the reward appointed to be paid firſt to thoſe, who were called at the eleventh hour, be given to the idle and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent? By no means: for theſe
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:31335:52"/> workmen were not called that they might be idle, but rather, they were rebuked, that they ſpent almoſt the whole day in Sloth and Idleneſs. Why, ſaith the good Man of the Houſe, ſtand ye here all day Idle? Now they are call'd idle, who have no work, no buſineſs to do; as the Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> employed by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſt does clearly import.</p>
               <p>Therefore they who were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and ſent into the Vineyard at the Eleventh hour, were not called to an idle lazy Faith only, but to the exerciſe of a lively Faith in obedience to the Will and Commands of him that called them, and to labour in the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard no leſs than they who were called before them, whoſe Faith hath been proved and tried in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers works, much labour and pain.
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:31335:52"/> This appears evidently by the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of thoſe who came firſt, delivered in that excellent Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; who affirmed that the laſt wrought but one hour, They ſaid not, that they who were called at that hour, were idle in the Vineyard, but that they wrought: it was favour and bounty enough ſhewn them by the good Man of the Houſe, that having wrought leſs, and being excuſed from the heat and burden of the day, they firſt of all were rewarded by the gracious bounty of the Lord, who is willing to give to the laſt, as to the firſt.</p>
               <p>From what hath been ſaid then, it is manifeſt and clear, that an imputative Faith, only laying hold of the Promiſes, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe lazy and unactive, is not that Faith which God does require of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:31335:53"/> thoſe, whom he calls to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints, and Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the Kingdom of Heaven; but a lively Faith, and ſuch as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſeth Believers in the Obedience and Obſervation of thoſe things that are commanded by him that calleth them. For as it is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to lay hold on the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes barely by Faith, unleſs we actually enjoy and poſſeſs the ſame; ſo it is not enough neither, to anſwer the Call by Faith alone, unleſs we alſo pay Obedience to him that hath called us. What Man is he that will ſay that it is enough for him, to enter into the Kingdom of Heaven by Faith, that is, by believing, tho he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver attain to the actual fruition and enjoyment of the Kingdom of God? Did God do ſo with the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> and the Seed of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:31335:53"/> that the Promiſes which they laid hold on by Faith were never made good unto them? No: for the bleſſing of God whom they believed and obeyed, they obtained the enjoyment and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the earthly Promiſes. Of <hi>Abraham</hi> a great Nation was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally made, and from one <hi>Iſaac,</hi> in whom God would have his Seed to be called, there ſprang ſo great a People, that <hi>Moſes</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed: <hi>Deut. 1. I am not able to bear you my ſelf alone: The Lord your God hath multiplied you, and behold you are this day as the Stars of Heaven for multitude. The Lord God of your Fathers make you a thouſand times ſe many as you are, and bleſs you, as he hath promiſed you.</hi> The People that were brought out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in Faith and Holy Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:31335:54"/> did actually obtain and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs the promiſed Land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> as it is written: <hi>Joſh. 1. Ariſe, go over this</hi> Jordan, <hi>thou and all this People, unto the Land which I do give to them, even to the Children of</hi> Iſrael. <hi>Every place that the ſole of your foot ſhall tread upon, that have I given unto you, as I ſaid unto</hi> Moſes. <hi>From the Wilderneſs and this Lebanon, even unto the great River, the River</hi> Euphrates, <hi>all the Land of the Hittites, and unto the great Sea toward the going down of the Sun, ſhall be your Coaſt.</hi> God not long after confirmed the truth of all this. <hi>Joſh. 24. I have given you a Land for which ye did not labour, and Cities which ye built not, and ye dwell in them: of the Vineyards and Oliveyards which ye planted not do ye eat. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> alſo believing the promiſe
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:31335:54"/> that he ſhould obtain the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, endured and overcame the hardeſt of times and dangers, and having at length obtained the Kingdom, thus did ſing: <hi>Pſal. 116. I believed, therefore have I ſpoken: I was greatly afflicted. I ſaid in my haſt; all Men are li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars. What ſhall I render unto the Lord for all his Benefits towards me?</hi> &amp;c. So that all theſe Ancients not only by Faith laid hold on the earthly Promiſes, but really obtained them, through the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God that promiſed to fulfil them to thoſe who believed and obeyed him: And therefore they obeyed the Law-giver not by Faith, and in words only, but with all care and dutifulneſs they alſo practiſed true Piety, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the Precepts and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, nor did any of thoſe
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:31335:55"/> who expected the deſired Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, think or ſay it was enough for him, that his fore-fathers, Predeceſſors, or Friends had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed the Commands and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of God, unleſs he himſelf did his duty, in obeying and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling the Law. <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelf being called went out. <hi>David</hi> being anointed King, and having obtained a Promiſe of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, believed, did, and ſuffered all thoſe things which we read with admiration. So alſo, that we may return to our ſelves, if we deſire, as we ought to do, to be truly and indeed, made partakers of the Spiritual Promiſes; if we have a real love for our ſelves, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire to everlaſting bliſs, we muſt not only believe the Promiſes, but likewiſe in all ſincerity practiſe Piety, and perform our ſeveral
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:31335:55"/> duties in obeying thoſe things that are enjoyned and commanded us: Nor muſt we think it enough, that Chriſt hath fulfilled for us the Law and all Righteouſneſs; unleſs believing in Chriſt, we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſubmit to that part of the Law which belongs to us, to wit, the Precepts and Commands of the <hi>Decalogue,</hi> wherein is comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the ſumm of the Will of God, and Law of Nature, and to what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever may be lawfully deduced and inferred from thence; and ſo obey the Law, that we may not be called Hearers only or Readers, Interpreters or Expounders there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but rather Doers of the ſame, and become like to thoſe, of whom it is written, <hi>Luke 1. And they were both righteous before God, walking in all the Commandments and Ordinances of the Lord blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs.</hi>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:31335:56"/> Rom. 2. <hi>For not the Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Law, are Juſt before God: but the doers of the Law ſhall be juſtified.</hi> Wherefore whoſoever being called to the Marriage of the Son, deſires to approve him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf faithfully to him that calleth him; He is chiefly to mind that there is nothing hidden from him who ſearcheth the ſecrets of the heart and reins, and knoweth the thoughts of Men afar off. And therefore let him ſeriouſly ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the duty of true and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned Repentance, and being grieved for all the offences of his ill-ſpent, wicked paſt life, let him with a contrite and humble heart, ſincerely confeſs his ſins and plead guilty in the preſence of God, and his Church, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the lawful Miniſters of the Church; Piouſly and Religiouſly
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:31335:56"/> obey the Counſels, Admonitions and Inſtructions that are given him, and having received Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Abſolution from the ſins and wickedneſs, which he hath promiſed to God, and to his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter as a Witneſs, and Judge up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth, to forſake; let him turn with all his mind and might, from that wicked life and filthy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, from all impure thoughts, all Guile, Malice and corrupt Manners; and then ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſhaken off and overcome the Temptations of Pride, Vanity, Covetouſneſs, Luſt, Earthly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and Pleaſures, and of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever may, and is wont to turn Men from God; let him conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſiſt in the right way, and by diligent and frequent Prayer call upon God, and beg his favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and gracious aſſiſtance, whoſe
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:31335:57"/> Mercy and provident care over him, he will to his experience cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly find, if from a pure and holy heart he earneſtly craves the ſame: For no leſs hath been offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and promiſed to all ſinners, by him who willeth not, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth their death, but that rather they may repent and live. <hi>Jer. 3. Return ye back-ſliding children, and I will heal your back-ſlidings.</hi> Jer. 4. <hi>If thou wilt return, O Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, ſaith the Lord, return unto me, and if thou wilt put away thine abominations out of my ſight, then ſhalt thou not remove. O</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem <hi>waſh thine heart from wicked<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſs, that thou mayeſt be ſaved: How long ſhall thy vain thoughts lodge within thee?</hi> Jer. 29. <hi>For I know the thoughts that I think to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, ſaith the Lord, thoughts of peace and not of evil, to give
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:31335:57"/> you an expected end. Then ſhall ye call upon me, and ye ſhall go and pray unto me, and I will hearken unto you. And ye ſhall ſeek me and find me, when ye ſhall ſearch for me with all your heart. And I will be found of you, ſaith the Lord.</hi> And again, <hi>Joel 2. Turn ye unto me with all your heart, and with faſting, and with weeping, and with mourning. And rent your heart, and not your garments, and turn unto the Lord your God: for he is gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and merciful, ſlow to anger, and of great kindneſs, and repenteth him of the evil.</hi> Nevertheleſs we muſt always be upon our guard, and take diligent heed, leſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely truſting to paſt Pardons and the confident expectation of Gods future mercy, we never ceaſe to do evil, and learn to do good: that is not the uſe, but the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:31335:58"/> abuſe of divine Clemency and Mercy. The Mercy of God is, indeed, from Generation to Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; but upon thoſe that fear him, and I will hear, ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal. 85. what God the Lord will ſay: for he will ſpeak Peace unto the People, and to his Saints: but let them not return a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to Folly.</hi> Again, <hi>Iſai as</hi> ſaith, <hi>Iſa. 30. Therefore will the Lord wait that he may be gracious unto you.</hi> The Lord will wait that he may be gracious, ſaith he, not that they who are waited for, ſhould heap ſin upon ſin, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn unto the vomit; but becauſe he hath promiſed mercy to them who with their whole heart ſo turn unto him, that they ſtand in awe, and greatly fear any more to offend him: otherwiſe, as the ſame Prophet ſaith, <hi>Therefore
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:31335:58"/> will the Lord be exalted that he may have Mercy upon you: for the Lord is a God of Judgment,</hi> who denies not his promiſed Mercy to any that rightly ſeek it, but withall does not for ever delay, but in due time inflict the puniſhments, which are appointed to thoſe whoſe heart is not right and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt with him. There is no time with God void of Mercy towards thoſe who hinder not their own Mercy; Now they do hinder it, who after the hardneſs and impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitence of their heart, treaſure up to themſelves wrath againſt the day of wrath. <hi>Iſa. 66. To this Man will I look,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>even to him that is poor, and of a contrite ſpirit, and trembleth at my word.</hi> But concerning thoſe who are not truly poor, of a contrite ſpirit, and tremble at his word,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:31335:59"/> he hath pronounc'd this Sentence: <hi>He that killeth an Ox, is as if he flew a Man: he that Sacrificeth a Lamb, as if he cut off a Dogs neck, he that Offereth an Oblation, as if he Offered Swines Blood; he that burneth Incenſe, as if he bleſſed an Idol:</hi> 1 Kings 8. <hi>they have choſen their own ways, and their Soul de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth in their abominations.</hi> They therefore that have committed ſin (for, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, there is no Man that ſinneth not) muſt conſtantly keep in the way of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and denying themſelves, hear and follow him, who hath ſaid; <hi>Not he that beginneth, but he that endureth to the end, the ſame ſhall be ſaved.</hi> They muſt from their whole heart and Soul, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the Devil and all his works, the pomps, and vanities
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:31335:59"/> of this wicked world, as they have promiſed and vowed in their Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm: otherwiſe, <hi>Jer. 8. thus, ſaith the Lord, ſhall they fall, and not ariſe? ſhall he turn away and not return? why then is this People of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>ſlidden back, by a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual back-ſliding?</hi> The Lord calls it a perpetual back-ſliding, when men in their manners, retain and follow that wicked courſe of life, which in word or thought they may have condemned, and falſly profeſſing and boaſting of their Repentance, do not conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly perform the duty of it, but belying their own hearts, deceive themſelves, and not God nor his Miniſter, to whom they promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a ſerious amendment of life: This the Lord finds fault with, by the ſame Prophet. <hi>They hold faſt deceit, they refuſe to return, I
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:31335:60"/> hearkned and heard, but they ſpake not aright: no Man repented him of his wickedneſs, ſaying, what have I done? Every one turned to his Courſe, as the Horſe ruſheth into the Battel.</hi> The Lord, indeed, waits that he may have mercy upon us, and uſes patience, not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to Repentance. Come to Repentance, ſaith that Apoſtle, who knew that Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance was neceſſary to ſinners, for appeaſing the wrath, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the mercy of God. Now the Holy Spirit does plainly tell us, that the long-ſuffering of God is not everlaſting, tho we believe and confeſs his Mercy to be infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite. <hi>Pſal. 7. God Judgeth the Righteous, and God is angry with the Wicked every day; if he turn not, he will whet his. Sword: he
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:31335:60"/> hath bent his Bow, and made it rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, he hath alſo prepared for him the inſtruments of death: He or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daineth his arrows againſt the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors.</hi> When God Almighty was about to deſtroy the old World, becauſe of ſin, he allotted them a certain time to repent in; as it is written, <hi>Gen, 6. And the Lord ſaid, my Spirit ſhall not always ſtrive with Man, for that he alſo is Fleſh: yet his days ſhall be an hundred and twenty years.</hi> At the end of which all Mankind periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Flood, ſave only the Family of <hi>Noah,</hi> who in that Age was found Righteous in the ſight of God. The People of <hi>Niniveh</hi> being warned by the Prophet, that after forty days they ſhould be deſtroyed, delayed not their Repentance until the laſt day, but ſet about it ſo ſoon as they heard
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:31335:61"/> the denunciation; all that time, I ſay, was employed and ſpent in faſting and prayer, for averting the wrath of God, imploring di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine mercy and amending their ſinful lives: as it is written, <hi>Jona 3. And</hi> Jonah <hi>began to enter into the City a days Journey, and he cried, and ſaid, yet fourty days, and</hi> Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neveh <hi>ſhall be overthrown. So the People of</hi> Nineveh <hi>believed God, and Proclaimed a Faſt, and put on Sackcloth from the greateſt of them even to the leaſt of them: for word came unto the King of</hi> Nineveh, <hi>and he aroſe from his Throne, and he laid his Robe from him, and covered him with Sackcloth, and ſate in Aſhes, and he cauſed to be proclaimed and publiſhed through</hi> Nineveh, (<hi>by the Decree of the King and his Nobles) ſaying, let neither Man nor Beaſt, Herd nor
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:31335:61"/> Flock taſt any thing; let them not feed nor drink water. But let Man and Beaſt be covered with Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth; and cry mightily unto God; yea let them turn every one from their evil way, and from the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence that is in their hands. Who can tell if God will turn and repent, and turn away from his fierce anger, that we periſh not? and God ſaw their works, that they turned from their evil way, and God repented of the evil that he had ſaid, that he would do unto them, and he did it not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Men of <hi>Nineveh</hi> will riſe in Judgment againſt thoſe who having been warned not once, but often, yet have not turned from their evil ways; or who have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed the duty of a ſerious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, to the laſt day of their life, living in the mean time wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:31335:62"/> and following the Vanities, Luſts, Ambition, Pride, and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the World: whereas no Man ought, or can ſay, that he is allowed to put off the exerciſe of Repentance to the extremity of life; ſince upon the firſt call and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, all Men are command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to turn and be converted unto the Lord. <hi>To day,</hi> ſaith the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, <hi>if you will hear his voice, harden not your hearts.</hi> Heb. 4. <hi>Let us therefore fear,</hi> ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>leſt a Promiſe being left us of entring into his Reſt, any of you ſhould ſeem to come ſhort of it. For unto us was the Goſpel Preached, as well as unto them. Let us labour therefore to enter into that Reſt.</hi> Now he ſhall not enter, who o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyeth not the voice of him that calleth him, nor he be owned, who hath not lawfully ſtriven.
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:31335:62"/> 1 <hi>Cor. 9. Know ye not,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul, that they which run in a race, run all, but one winneth the prize? ſo run that you may obtain.</hi> We are to run and not go back, to run and not to ſtand ſtill, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Apoſtle; We are to run not ſlowly but lawfully; and with ſo much more the greater pains, diligence and care, by how much the Prize ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us is to be eſteemed and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before a Crown of Olive, Smallage, or Oak-leaves. Now what pains and labour they were at to exerciſe themſelves who were to run in the race, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Luxury might ſoften, nor Lazineſs dull them, they who have written on that Subject, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form us.</p>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:31335:63"/>
                  <l>Qui cupit optatam curſu contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere metam,</l>
                  <l>Multa tulit, fecitque puer, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>davit &amp; alſit,</l>
                  <l>Abſtinuit Venere &amp; vino, &amp;c.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Youth who ſtrives the wiſh'd goal to obtain,</l>
                  <l>Much anxious toil endures, colds, heats, and pain,</l>
                  <l>And Wine, and Women ſhuns, &amp;c.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>And they,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>are temperate in all things, that they may obtain a corruptible Crown: but we an incorruptible.</hi> Now it is manifeſt, that the long-ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and patience of God for the repentance of all and every ſinner, is limited within certain bounds; for after death there is no place
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:31335:63"/> for repentance, ſo that we muſt, (if ever) repent in this life. And therefore ſince experience it ſelf convinceth us of the ſhortneſs of life, beſides what divine wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom teacheth us, <hi>that Man is of few days, and the number of his months is with thee; Job</hi> 14. we ought to conſider the extent and limits of divine patience and long-ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and not to truſt to that dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous hope, which hath decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved many, who have deferred the thoughts of ſerious repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to the very laſt day of their life. For tho the uſe and improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life be left to the will and pleaſure of Man, yet the time and manner of death is not in his option. Now as the way and manner of living is two-fold, the one large and broad, and the other ſtrait and narrow: ſo it is
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:31335:64"/> left to Man to chooſe which of the two he pleaſeth; yet he is not only adviſed, but even command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to chooſe that which is beſt and ſafeſt; as it is written, <hi>Deut. 30. See, I have ſet before thee this day life and good, and death and evil, in that I command thee this day, to love the Lord thy God, to walk in his ways, and to keep his commandments, and his ſtatutes, and his judgments, that thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt live, &amp;c. Therefore chuſe life, that both thou and thy ſeed may live: that thou mayeſt love the Lord thy God, and that thou mayeſt obey his voice, and that thou mayeſt cleave unto him: for he is thy life, and the length of thy days.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now of the nine hundred and ſeven ways of death, which are obſerved to happen unto Man, without violence; it is not left
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:31335:64"/> to him to chooſe which of all he would ſubmit unto, but that is reſerved to the Providence and Will of God, in whoſe hands are the iſſues of death. It is great madneſs and folly then, and no leſs dangerous temerity, to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect thoſe things which are laid before us, as ſafe, certain, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to our view, and but few in number; and to ſet our minds on things that are remote, foreign to our happineſs, uncertain, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and various, and likewiſe moſt difficult. Again, who ſeeth not, how wicked a thing it is, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect and deſire that the deſigned and affected loſs of our whole life, ſhould be made up by the Prayer of a Minutes or leſs conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance at laſt? And that he ſhould look for the honour and prize of the race or fight, who
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:31335:65"/> hath neither run nor fought, when yet he might and ought to have done it? In a word, how is his judgment depraved who deſires wickedly and careleſly to live, and to die holily? Whatever others may think of this matter, I am little concerned: but am ſtill of opinion, and do affirm that ſuch opinions are full of danger, and that many have been thereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. If the inſtance of that ſinful woman, or of the Thief in the Goſpel be objected to us, we ſhall willingly admit of it for confirmation of the truth, and retort it back again. For that woman who was a ſinner in the City, when once ſhe had come to Chriſt, and found him merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; by a continued exerciſe of Repentance, and Sanctity of life for the future, ſhe ſecured to her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:31335:65"/> his favour and bleſſing: ſo far was ſhe from eſtranging him from her, by new ſins and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And the Thief at the ſame time that he was inſtructed in the truth of Chriſt, began a ſerious Repentance which with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant mind he continued till the laſt breath of his life, and would in all probability, have continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it longer, if either he had eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped death that day, or hung lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger alive upon the Croſs: whom that common torment of the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, made greater by the breaking of his legs, diverted not from the thoughts of his own Salvation, nor the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of his Saviour. And we have reaſon to think, that if he had known the grace and truth of Chriſt before, he would have forſaken his wicked courſes, and <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:31335:66"/> purpoſe of virtue and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, till the laſt day of his life? Is that to imitate the Thief, <hi>Mary Magdalene,</hi> or St. <hi>Peter?</hi> who coming to himſelf, acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his ſin, and avoiding that croud by whoſe company and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſes he had been drawn, and almoſt forc'd into his offence, went forth and wept bitterly, return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no more to thoſe who had been the occaſion of his Fall, but cleaving cloſe to the ſociety of the other Diſciples, whom both by example and diſcourſe he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in the hope of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Reſurrection; doing as his Lord commanded him: <hi>and thou, when thou art converted, ſtrengthen thy brethren.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are the inſtances of a Repentance moſt acceptable to God and profitable to Man, which
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:31335:66"/> whoſoever will ſeriouſly imitate to his own Salvation, muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce himſelf, that is, his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcenſes, the pomps and vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the World, reform the courſe of his life, walk carefully in the ways that God does ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of; and having taken up his croſs, with a lively Faith, and conſtant Obedience follow Chriſt, caſt off all impediments that may divert him from, or hinder him in his Journey, and always have in his mind what the Lord hath recommended to our ſerious pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice: <hi>Luke 9. If any Man will come after me, let him deny him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and take up his Croſs daily and folly me.</hi> Mat. 24. <hi>And he that ſhall endure unto the end, the ſame ſhall be ſaved. And no Man having put his hand to the plough, and looking back, is fit for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:31335:67"/> of God. He that hath ears to hear, let him hear; God deceiveth no Man.</hi> Let every one take heed then, that he deceive not himſelf, nor ſuffer himſelf to be deceived by others. This is the plain, ſure and ſafe way; that hath the promiſe of good ſucceſs; Repentance, I mean, which eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one ought carefully to ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, perſiſt in, and proſecute to the end. This is the way that never deceived any Man, but will certainly bring thoſe that walk therein to eternal Salvation at laſt. For it is written, <hi>Pſal. 69. Pſal. 105. Your hearts ſhall live that ſeek God. Seek the Lord and his ſtrength: ſeek his face ever more</hi> He that ſeeketh his face always in what manner ſoever he may end this mortal life, yet his Son ſhall live. <hi>Pſal. 9. For thou, Lord
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:31335:67"/> haſt not forſaken them that ſeek thee.</hi> The death of <hi>Lazarus</hi> was mean and obſcure in the eyes of Men, but that of the rich Man conſpicuous, and his Funeral pompous. <hi>The rich Man died and was buried:</hi> however the Soul of the former was received into <hi>Abraham</hi>'s boſom, when this Mans Soul was ſent down into Hell. Wherefore let thoſe who either never ſet about the work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance aright, or put it off to the hour of death, or often in their life-time begin it, and as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten again leave it off; let them, I ſay, conſider, what ground they have to do ſo, and what divine promiſe they can pretend to truſt to; for it is not in our power to command our time when we would, and whether God will grant it to us according to our
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:31335:68"/> wiſhes, is much to be doubted. As 'tis written: <hi>Thou haſt trodden down all them that err from thy Statutes: for their deceit is falſhood.</hi> No Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of the Chriſtian Church, (for what I know) ever taught us to put off and delay Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and amendment of life, till the laſt day of living; nor promiſed any happy ſucceſs to thoſe that did ſo; nay St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> doubts of the condition of thoſe delayers of ſerious Repentance, till the hour of death, and we have no reaſon but, with St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin,</hi> to doubt of the ſame. <hi>Wo be to fearful hearts, and faint hands, and the ſinner that goeth two ways.</hi> Wo will be unto many to whom opportunity and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of amending their lives has been offered and granted, whilſt they were alive and in
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:31335:68"/> health, and whilſt God waited for them, and who ſtill perſiſting in their wickedneſs, their too late deſire of Repentance, will through their own fault, be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable to them. Many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of wicked Men, who die without Repentance happen dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; ſome ſnatcht away by ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den death, others killed, ſome caſt away at Sea, others ſlain in Battel, or brought to their end by thunder, lightning, and many other ways: who, perhaps, if their lives had been longer, would have ſeriouſly ſet about the work of Repentance; but it hath ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed otherwiſe to the Judgment and Decree of God, who, ſeeing he does all that is neceſſary for reclaiming of ſinners, is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways wont to ſuperadd more than ought to be expected, <hi>Mat.</hi>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:31335:69"/> 11. Had God done <hi>the mighty works in</hi> Tyre <hi>and</hi> Sidon, <hi>which he did in</hi> Chorazin <hi>and</hi> Bethſaida, he knew, that <hi>they would have repented in Sack-cloth and aſhes. And if the mighty works which were done in</hi> Capernaum, <hi>had been done in</hi> Sodom, it alſo, upon the word of our Saviour, <hi>would have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained until this day.</hi> But ſeeing the Almighty had done for thoſe places what was enough, in his moſt righteous Judgment, he was not willing to add more than was ſufficient. How many of thoſe, who have led a wicked and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful life, and ſtill profeſſed an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination and deſire to die well, have either had the death they wiſhed for, or a bleſſed and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py end? How every Man ſhall end his days, depends not on himſelf, but on the Counſel and
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:31335:69"/> Decree of God; as it is written, <hi>Pſal. 68. He that is our God, is the God of Salvation, and unto God the Lord belong the iſſues from death. But God ſhall wound the head of his enemies: and the hairy ſcalp of ſuch a one as goeth on ſtill in his Treſpaſſes.</hi> Moſt terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble alſo, and yet moſt certain, is that Sentence pronounced by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Oracle. <hi>Pſal. 34. Evil ſhall ſlay the wicked: and they that hate the righteous ſhall be deſolate.</hi> But great are the Promiſes and hopes that the Scripture gives to thoſe who love piety, and are of a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent and obedient heart, which we ſhould always have before our eyes. <hi>The Lord redeemeth the Soul of his Servants, and none of them that truſt in him ſhall be deſolate.</hi> Let us then a little conſider, what theſe Men do, who leaving off to <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:31335:70"/> after he had left his<note place="margin">The Example of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
                  </note> Country, Kindred, and Fathers Houſe, never returned again into <hi>Chaldea</hi> or <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi> but travelled and So journed in ſeveral places, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the will and appointment of God, ſpending his whole life, even to death, in the obedience of Gods commands, and that he would not die, nor be buried any where, but there where he had received the Promiſes: nor move a foot from thoſe places, wherein he was warned from Heaven to tarry and abide. Wherefore the Holy Scripture ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhing thoſe who are the true children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> that is, his ſpiritual Children, who is called the Father of many Nations, of their duty, in imitation of their fathers example, ſaith: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:31335:70"/> 
                  <hi>Hearken to me, ye that follow af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter righteouſneſs, ye that ſeek the Lord: look unto the rock whence ye are hewen, and to the hole of the pit whence ye are digged. Look unto</hi> Abraham <hi>your Father, and unto</hi> Sarah <hi>that bare you; for I called him alone, and bleſſed him, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed him:</hi> as being a Man who firmly believed, and diligently obeyed God that called him, <hi>Col. 3. So then they which be of the Faith,</hi> (and imitate the example of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham) are bleſſed with faithful</hi> Abraham.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, my dear fellow Chriſtians, being furniſhed with all theſe precepts and inſtructions of God the Father, and of his Son Jeſus Chriſt our Lord and Maſter, let us in the firſt place, take diligent heed that we ſin not. For that indeed is beſt: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:31335:71"/> all the Sons of <hi>Adam</hi> are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſin, the wiſeſt counſel and moſt acceptable to God, that can be given, in the next place is, that he who hath ſinned, would with all his heart and mind turn to God: 1 <hi>John 2. for we have an advocate with the Father, Jeſus Chriſt the Righteous: and he is the propitiation for our ſins: and not for ours only, but alſo for the ſins of the whole world.</hi> If he be ſought of us with a contrite and humble heart: which the Lord himſelf declares: <hi>To this Man will I look, even to him that is poor and of a contrite ſpirit, and trembleth at my word.</hi> Wherefore the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle St. <hi>John</hi> admoniſhes us, ſaying, 1 <hi>John 3. Beloved, if our heart condemn us not, then have we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence towards God. And whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we ask, we receive of him,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:31335:71"/> becauſe we keep his commandments, and do thoſe things that are pleaſing in his ſight.</hi> St. <hi>John</hi> expreſsly affirms, that we ſhall obtain what we ask of God in order to our Salvation, who will give his good ſpirit to thoſe that ſeek him, if our heart condemn us not: which he ſaith may be proved by this, if we keep his command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and do thoſe things that are pleaſing in his ſight. Our Lord and Maſter commands the ſame: <hi>John 14. If ye love me, keep my commandments. And I will pray the Father, and he ſhall give you another comforter, that he may abide with you for ever; even the ſpirit of truth, whom the world can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not receive;</hi> ſeein the Luſt, and Pride, the Pomp and Vanity, with all the other Vices of this World are an abomination to him:
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:31335:72"/> 2 <hi>Tim. 2. But if a Man purge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from theſe, he ſhall be a Veſſel unto Honour, ſanctified and meet for the Maſters uſe, and prepared unto every good work.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſum then of all that hath been ſaid, in ſhort is this, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever with a pure and holy heart believes the promiſes of God to his own ſalvation, let him ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly renounce the pomps and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of this World, and the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Luſts and Deſires of the Fleſh, and make good his profeſſion of Repentance, by a true and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt forſaking of all ſin and vice, and a following after Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and obedience to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God with a zealous and conſtant care. Of this care we ſhall ſpeak hereafter, having firſt laid down for a certain truth, (which we cannot inculcate too
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:31335:72"/> often) that the holy ſpirit can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not dwell in a heart polluted with the ſinful luſts, pleaſures, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther corruptions of the fleſh, the ſpirit, I ſay, of ſanctification, by which, who are acted, are the Sons of God. For this is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs ſentence of God Almighty himſelf, which hath been alledged already, and ought often to be cited: <hi>Gen. My ſpirit ſhall not always ſtrive with Man, for that he alſo is Fleſh.</hi> that is to ſay, ſo long as Man is fleſh, and obeys the will and luſts of the fleſh, he ſhall not be partaker of my ſpirit. And this ſentence was pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by God, at that time when the Sons of God coming in unto the Daughters of Men, perverted all the rules of Piety and Virtue, and turned Righteouſneſs into Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Now they who believed the
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:31335:73"/> Promiſes of God made unto <hi>Adam</hi> the common Parent of Mankind, and being endowed with that Faith, exerciſed themſelves in the practice of Piety, are in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture called the Sons of God: for amongſt them was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the knowledg of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption and Salvation of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind by the holy Seed of the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: and they being animated with the Faith and Hope of this promiſed Salvation, ſhunned all worldly ambition and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, leading a life neither magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent nor ſplendid, nor attended with the glory and delights, which Men admire, but low, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, and mean, living in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry habitations of cottages, tents, caves and dens, and were ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſober poverty, in imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their common Parents <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi>
                  <pb n="139" facs="tcp:31335:73"/> and <hi>Eve,</hi> whom God, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving cloathed them with coats made of Beaſts skins, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to live contented, willing that they who by their own fault had forfeited the ſovereignty of the World, ſhould live like ſtrangers and ſojourners in it. This exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the Sons of God followed. But on the other hand, the Sons of Men, who either believed not the divine Promiſes, or lived in pomp and ſplendor, gave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves over to delights and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, courted glory and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly greatneſs; and built to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſtately Houſes, Towns and Caſtles; being not a little in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited to that courſe of life, by the humour and counſel of Women; by whoſe blandiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and converſation, the Sons of God alſo being firſt allured,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:31335:74"/> and then wholly overcome, <hi>they took to themſelves wives of all which they choſe:</hi> That is to ſay, when the Sons of God perceived the delights and pleaſures, the pomp and ſplendor that was amongſt Men, which might tempt humane frailty to prefer them before the rigours of an auſtere frugality; but eſpecially being enticed by the ſight of Women, among whom Vanity and Luxury, both in diet and apparel, was moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous, they forſook the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips of an auſtere life, continence and poverty, that they might em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace riches, wealth, pleaſures and luxury; and making Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages with the Daughters of Men, they overturned Piety, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted the antient diſcipline of primitive virtue and integrity. Whereupon that divine Sentence
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:31335:74"/> was pronounced: <hi>My ſpirit ſhall not always ſtrive with Man, for that he alſo is fleſh:</hi> becauſe of the Sons of God, they not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came like unto the Sons of Men, but begat a race much more cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt than themſelves, more licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious in their lives, indulging themſelves in all ſorts of vice and voluptuouſneſs, and prone to all kind of injuſtice, barbarity and cruelty, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. Theſe are the <hi>Giants which were in the Earth in thoſe days; and alſo after that, when the Sons of God came in unto the Daughters of Men, and they bare children unto them: the ſame became mighty Men, which were of old Men of Renown. And God ſaw that the wickedneſs of Man was great in the Earth, and that every imagination of the thoughts of his heart was only evil
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:31335:75"/> continually. And it repented the Lord that he had made Man on the Earth.</hi> So much did the licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wickedneſs of the diſſolute life of Men offend God, that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Oracles aſſure us, it repented him that he had made Man on the Earth; and that he reſolved to deſtroy all Mankind, theſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excepted, who continued in the diſcipline and duty of the Sons of God, tho they were but very few in number; as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; But <hi>Noah</hi> found grace in the eyes of the Lord, becauſe he was a Juſt Man; being not only endowed with that Faith of the Sons of God; but through the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of true Repentance, and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the commandments of God, accepted alſo of the Lord: as one who having ſpent ſo many years in building of an
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:31335:75"/> Ark, and by frequent Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons forewarning the Men of that age of the imminent wrath of God, endeavoured to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them to Repentance and amendment of life, for which he got the title and name of <hi>a Preacher of Righteouſneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, this practice of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance which, as we have ſaid, is neceſſary to all the Diſciples and followers of Chriſt, muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with an endeavour of amendment of life, and of fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing after Righteouſneſs and <hi>Honeſty;</hi> which, for illuſtration ſake, we ſhall call by the name of <hi>Obedience;</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine<note place="margin">Obedience.</note> Obedience to be an <hi>ordering and framing of all the actions of our life, according to the counſel and will of God.</hi> And this is performed by the knowledg
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:31335:76"/> and diligent practice of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God. For it is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to know the precepts and inſtitutions of our Chriſtian diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, or to talk of, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them in quaint and elegant language, unleſs we alſo careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſtudiouſly practiſe and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them: This is the expreſs Doctrine of our Lord and Maſter, <hi>Mat. 7. Not every one that ſaith unto me, Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the Kingdom of Heaven: but he that doth the will of my Father which is in Heaven. Many will ſay unto me in that day, Lord, Lord, have we not propheſied in thy name? and in thy name caſt out Devils? and in thy name done many won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful works? and then I will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs unto them, I never knew you: depart from me ye that work ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. Therefore, whoſoever hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:31335:76"/> theſe ſayings of mine, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them, I will liken him unto a wife Man which built his houſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Rock: and the Rain deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Floods came, and the Winds blew, and beat upon that Houſe: and it fell not, for it was founded upon a Rock.</hi> We muſt, therefore, take care that the ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of our ſalvation be founded upon this Rock of true Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, leſt that after we have built much and long, ſome contrary guſt beating upon it, it fall to the ground. Now this Obedience is performed in obſerving the will of our heavenly Father, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Doctrine of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, ſaying: <hi>He that doeth the will of my Father, who is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> And the Father himſelf hath declared that his will is, that we ſhould know, hold faſt, and
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:31335:77"/> carefully practiſe the Doctrine of his deareſt Son. <hi>Mat. 17. This is my beloved Son in whom I am well pleaſed; hear ye him.</hi> If then we would deſire to know what we are to do for obtaining the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which this beloved Son hath brought into the World; let us ſeriouſly conſult him, who was propoſed, and confirmed to us by the Father in preſence of moſt reverend witneſſes, two of the Old and three of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as the wiſe and infallible interpreter of his Will; and we ſhall hear him thus anſwering and teaching us: <hi>John 15. If ye keep my commandments, ye ſhall abide in my love: even as I have kept my Fathers commandments, and abide in his love.</hi> John 14. <hi>He that hath my commandments, and keepeth them, he it is that loveth me; and
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:31335:77"/> he that loveth me ſhall be loved of my Father, and I will love him, and will manifeſt my ſelf to him:</hi> and again, <hi>Joh. 15. ye are my friends, if ye do whatſoever I command you.</hi> And elſewhere; <hi>Mat. 11. Take my yoke upon you, and learn of me, for I am meek and lowly in heart: and ye ſhall find reſt unto your ſouls. For my yoke is eaſie, and my burthen is light.</hi> By which words we are plainly taught, that the deſired reſt of our ſouls cannot be found, but by thoſe who do the Will of the Father. Now, for diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Will, the Father him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf referred us to the hearing of his Son: and the Son tells us, that it is his Fathers Will, that they who would find reſt to their Souls, ſhould take his yoke upon them, and that his yoke is neither hard nor heavy, but ſoft and eaſie,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:31335:78"/> and that his burden, that is, the ſum of the Doctrine of the Law and Commandments, is a light burden. And indeed, the thing it ſelf not only ſpeaks it to be ſo, but the noble inſtances alſo of many, who have ſubmitted to that yoke fully confirm it. For the yoke we ſpeak of, is no more but that ſincere and brotherly love, which by another name, is commonly called charity: as our Lord and Maſter does frequently inculcate. <hi>John 15. This is my commandment that ye love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as I have loved you. Theſe things I command you that ye love one another.</hi> And he affirms this conſtant and perpetual precept to be ſo properly and peculiarly his own, that he would have it to be the badg and mark of his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and followers. <hi>John</hi> 13.
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:31335:78"/> 
                  <hi>A new Commandment I give unto you, that ye love one another; as I have loved you, that ye alſo love one another. By this ſhall all Men know that ye are my Diſciples, if ye love one another.</hi> St. <hi>John</hi> the great Diſciple and Witneſs of our Lord and Maſter, again and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain confirms this: 1 <hi>John 3. Beloved, if our heart condemn us not, then have we confidence towards God; and whatſoever we ask we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of him, becauſe we keep his commandments, and do thoſe things that are pleaſing in his ſight. And this is his commandment, that we ſhould believe on the name of his Son Jeſus Chriſt, and love one another, as he gave us commandment.</hi> And of how great neceſſity the keeping of this commandment is, the ſame Apoſtle fully demonſtrates unto us. 1 <hi>John 2. He that hateth his
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:31335:79"/> brother, is in darkneſs, and walketh in darkneſs, and knoweth not whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he goeth, becauſe that dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs hath blinded his eyes.</hi> This is ſo true and plain a Doctrine of Chriſtian Religion, that that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Expoſitor of the divine Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, made no ſcruple to prefer this love before all the other vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, acts and endowments of the mind of Man. 1 <hi>Cor. 13. Though I ſpeak with the tongues of Men and of Angels, and have not Charity, I am become as ſounding braſs, or a tinkling Cimbal. And tho I have the gift of propheſie, and underſtand all myſteries, and all knowledge; and tho I have all Faith, ſo that I could remove Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and have not Charity, I am nothing. And tho I beſtow all my goods to feed the poor, and though I give my body to be burned, and
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:31335:79"/> have not Charity, it profiteth me nothing.</hi> And ſo far is Charity commended by this Apoſtle, that he calls it, <hi>Col. 3. the bond of perfectneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now if Charity be ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that without it, the Apoſtle affirms all things elſe to be unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to ſalvation; how far is he from ſalvation, who not only loves not his brother, but even hates and perſecutes him? if he who loves not, baniſhes from himſelf the love of God, in what condition is he, and how ſhall he be eſteemed in the eyes of God, that hateth his brother? No leſs than a Murderer; and according to the ſentence of the holy word of God he is guilty of that crime. <hi>John 3. Whoſoever hateth his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is a Murderer:</hi> in thought and affection, which God chiefly takes
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:31335:80"/> notice of, he is accounted a Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer, who loveth not his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and ye know, ſaith he, <hi>that no Murderer hath eternal life abiding in him.</hi> As elſewhere: <hi>He that hateth his brother, walketh in darkneſs.</hi> Wherefore St. <hi>James</hi> admoniſheth Chriſtians, leſt being corrupted with this vice, which under ſome diſguiſe or other uſes to creep and ſteal into mens minds they ſhould make void the name and profeſſion of Religion, and ſo deceive themſelves or others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>James 3. But if ye have bitter envying and ſtrife in your hearts, glory not; and lie not againſt the truth,</hi> (Calling and boaſting your ſelves to be Chriſtians) <hi>This wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom deſcendeth not from above; but is earthly ſenſual, diviliſh. For where envying and ſtrife is, there is confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and every evil work. But the wiſdom that is from above, is
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:31335:80"/> firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle, and eaſie to be intreated, full of mercy and good fruits, without partiality, and without hypocriſie.</hi> We are alſo plainly and largely taught by our Lord and Maſter, how grievous a ſin the ſin of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred is, and how great an impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment it lays in our way to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, not only when it appears outwardly in evil deeds, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven when but conceited inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the heart. <hi>Mat. 5. I ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, that whoſoever is angry with his brother without a cauſe, ſhall be in danger of the Judgment, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall ſay to his brother, Raca, ſhall be in danger of the Council: but whoſoever ſhall ſay, thou fool,</hi> (to wit, moved with anger, and with deſign to hurt him) <hi>ſhall be in danger of hell fire.</hi> Wherefore our Lord and Maſter in his divine wiſdom, that he might ſhew how
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:31335:81"/> expedient it is to be free from that vice and perturbation of mind, plainly tells his Diſciples, that he who hath not firſt ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this command of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, muſt not think to obtain the favour of God by any Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice or other Religious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance. <hi>Therefore, if thou bring thy gift to the Altar, and there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreſt that thy brother hath ought againſt thee; leave thy gift before the Altar, and go thy way, firſt be reconciled to thy brother, and then come and offer thy gift.</hi> In many other paſſages he confirms the ſame, ſaying. <hi>Luke 6. Be ye mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful, as your Father alſo is merciful: forgive, and ye ſhall be forgiven: give, and it ſhall be given unto you. Bleſſed are the merciful, for they ſhall obtain mercy.</hi> Now the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity which our Lord ſo much commendeth, is not a cold and
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:31335:81"/> ordinary, but a burning and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent charity, ready to do good, whereby he bids us to become like unto God, who makes his Sun to ſhine upon the good and the bad, and cauſeth it to rain upon the juſt, and the unjuſt. And when our Saviour taught his Diſciples to pray, he enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged more upon the Subject of Charity, Mercy, and Beneficence, than upon any other; as being of all others the chief and moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing argument of Piety, which by the Apoſtle alſo, is called the bond o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> perfection: ſeeing all the commands and duties whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever of the Law, are eaſily obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and performed by thoſe, who are ſo quickned by Charity, as not ſo much to ſeek their own, as the things of others; accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as it is written. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:31335:82"/> 
                  <hi>Charity ſuffereth long, and is kind; Charity envieth not; Charity vaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not it ſelf; is not puffed up, doth not behave it ſelf unſeemly, ſeeketh not her own, is not eaſily provoked, thinketh no evil, rejoyceth not in iniquity, but rejoyceth in the truth: beareth all things, believeth all things, hopeth all things, endureth all things.</hi> Whereas, 1 <hi>John. He that hateth his brother is in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and walketh in darkneſs, and knoweth not whither he goeth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that darkneſs hath blinded his eyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſumm then of all<note place="margin">The ſumm of the rule common to all Men.</note> that a Scholar of Chriſt ought to know, hold, meditate upon, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, is briefly comprehended un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe three Heads, to wit, the Fear of the Lord, Repentance, and Charity. Now Charity is
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:31335:82"/> not here conſidered only as it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to God, whom we ought to love above all things, but alſo as it is to be practiſed towards Men. 1 <hi>John 3. Hereby perceive we the love of God, becauſe he laid down his life for us: and we ought to lay down our lives for the brethren. But whoſa hath this Worlds good, and ſeeth his brother have need, and ſhutteth up his bowels of compaſſion from him, how dwelleth the love of God in him? My little children, let us not love in word neither in tongue, but in deed and in truth. And hereby we know that we are of the truth, and ſhall aſſure our hearts before him.</hi> 1 John 4. <hi>Let us love him; becauſe he firſt loved us. If a Man ſay, I love God, and hateth his brother, he is a liar, for he that loveth not his brother whom he hath ſeen, how can he love God whom he
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:31335:83"/> hath not ſeen? and this command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have we from him, that he who loveth God, love his brother alſo.</hi> Whoever, therefore ſhall care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully obſerve theſe three heads, will by experience find the mercy, goodneſs, and clemency of God towards him; the excellency whereof the thought of Man is not able to conceive, and far leſs his tongue to expreſs. For the gracious God is always ready to fulfill the promiſes of ſalvation, which have been made and often confirmed to Believers; as it is written. <hi>Jer. 18. At what inſtant I ſhall ſpeak concerning a Nation, and concerning a Kingdom to pluck up, and to pull down, and to deſtroy it: if that Nation againſt whom I have pronounced, turn from their evil, I will repent of the evil that I though to do unto them. Ezek.</hi> 18.
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:31335:83"/> And <hi>if the wicked will turn from all his ſins that he hath committed, and keep all my ſtatutes, and do that which is lawful and right, he ſhall ſurely live, he ſhall not die. All his tranſgreſſions that he hath committed, they ſhall not be menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned unto him: in his righteouſneſs that he hath done, he ſhall live. Have I any pleaſure at all that the wicked ſhould die? ſaith the Lord: and not that he ſhould return from his ways and live?</hi> So that the Oracles of God do often confirm the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of life and ſalvation made even to wicked Men who turn from their ways; to thoſe I ſay, who turning from the evil of their way, and following a courſe of true Repentance, make it their care and ſtudy to obey the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God, and to do Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Juſtice; for whoever
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:31335:84"/> do ſo, ſhall live; not by an idle, laſie and unactive Faith, which is alſo called a dead Faith; but through the righteouſneſs which they have wrought, they ſhall, indeed, obtain life and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, from God the author and fountain of life, which he hath promiſed to all who believe in him, and obey his world, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that infinite mercy of his, which the Scripture celebrates in many places. <hi>Pſal. 145. The lord is gracious and full of compaſſion; ſlow to anger, and of great mercy.</hi> The Lord is good to all: and his tender mercies are over all his works. And therefore he bears with the ſins of men, that he may bring them to Repentance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wiſdom. 11. For he loveth all the things that are, and abhorreth nothing that he hath made: for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:31335:84"/> would he have made any thing, if he had hated it.</hi> And therefore it is, that he freely offers and promiſes his mercy unto all, who with a true heart and purpoſe of mind deſire to be converted, and to return to him, as it is written. <hi>Ezek. 33. As I live, ſaith the Lord God, I have no pleaſure in the death of the wicked, but that the wicked turn from his way and live: turn ye, turn turn ye from your evil ways, for why will ye die, O Houſe of Iſrael?</hi> For the Lord is moſt gracious, and deſirous of our ſalvation, who, when he would have Men to turn to him with their whole heart and mind, and ſo obtain life, he patiently waits for their Repentance: and this the holy Scriptures clearly teſtifie. <hi>Iſa. 30. Therefore will the Lord wait, that he may be graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:31335:85"/> unto you, and therefore will he be exalted, that he may have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon you.</hi> And the Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith: <hi>The Lord is not ſlack concerning his Promiſe (as ſome Men count ſlackneſs) but is long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering to us-ward, not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to repentance.</hi> Now that the Converſion and true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance of ſinners, is moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable and pleaſing to God, his own Son ſhews us, in that ſaving Sermon which he made in the three Parables of the prodigal Son, the loſt ſheep, and groat; whereby he exhorted all Men, that they would endeavour by their converſion to pleaſe God, and cauſe joy in the whole Court of Heaven, that ſo they might taſt of the wonderful goodneſs of God, who is rich in mercy towards
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:31335:85"/> all that call upon him with a pure and ſingle heart, and upon whom, if they approve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by Faith, and the practice of true Repentance and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, he beſtows great mercies, and the ſpirit of ſanctification with all his gifts and graces, which St. <hi>Peter</hi> affirms was given to all that obey him, and our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour promiſed to be given, ſaying: <hi>John 14. If ye love me, keep my commandments, And I will pray the Father, and he ſhall give you another comforter, that he may abide with you for ever; even the ſpirit of truth, whom the world can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not receive.</hi> Now in the ſence of St. <hi>John,</hi> the world are they who live according to the <hi>luſt of the eye, the luſt of the fleſh, or the pride of life;</hi> that is, who are ſlaves to luſt, delights, pleaſures, or ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:31335:86"/> for thoſe ſhall not feel the power and virtue of that holy ſpirit abiding in them: as the Lord himſelf pronounces; <hi>Gen. 6. My ſpirit ſhall not always ſtrive with Man, for that he alſo is fleſh.</hi> With Man who is fleſh, and ſtriveth not to mortifie the deeds of the Fleſh, as the Apoſtle ſaith: <hi>if ye live after the fleſh, ye ſhall die: but if ye through the ſpirit do mortifie the deeds of the body, ye ſhall live:</hi> to wit, through the ſpirit of God given and communicated unto you; for ſo it is written. <hi>Iſa. 66. Thus ſaith the Lord, the Heaven is my Throne, and the Earth is my Footſtool: where is the houſe that ye build unto me? and where is the place of my reſt? for all thoſe things hath mine hand made, and all thoſe things have been, ſaith the Lord: but to this Man will I look, even to
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:31335:86"/> him that is poor, and of a contrite ſpirit, and trembleth at my word.</hi> Thoſe divine gifts and graces whereby Men upon Earth are changed into other creatures, and become almoſt celeſtial, avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the corruption that is in the World through luſt, and having their converſation in heaven; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples and inſtances of theſe gifts, I ſay, which were very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent of old, are now rare to be found on the Earth: becauſe we have neither that ſtrong and lively faith in the Promiſes of God, nor purely and ſincerely obey his Precepts; neither are we filled with the holy fear of the Lord; but by a double and deceitful heart, wicked and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe thoughts and actions, we are wanting to our ſelves, and to the grace and goodneſs of God:
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:31335:87"/> of God, I ſay, <hi>who trieth the heart and ſearcheth the reins,</hi> and ſees us wholly given over to impure thoughts, the delights and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the fleſh, and to pride and ambition, like adulterous Women dealing treacheroſly againſt their lawful husbands; which kind of hearts eſtranged from, or divided in their chief love, he neither loves nor ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves of. The mind muſt be pure and ſingle, and fervent in love, that aſpires to the heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly marriage of this bridegroom and would have it confirmed and made good to it. The wiſe Son of <hi>Sirach</hi> adviſes us to endeavour that as much as we can, when he ſaith. <hi>Ecclus 1. 2. Diſtruſt not the fear of the Lord: and come not unto him with a double heart. Wo be to fearful hearts, and faint hands,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:31335:87"/> and the ſinner that goeth two ways.</hi> And the word of God by the mouth of his holy Prophets, does alſo in many places expreſly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh us, heartily to renounce the vanities, ſins and pollutions of this World, and make it our whole care to forſake them. <hi>Jer. 4. O Jeruſalem, waſh thine heart from wickedneſs, that thou mayeſt be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: how long ſhall thy vain thoughts lodg within thee?</hi> Whoſoever come ſo provided to ſeek the Lord, ſhall certainly find him to be loving, gracious and bountiful. <hi>Jer. 29. Ye ſhall ſeek me, and find me, when ye ſhall ſearch for me with all your heart; and I will be found of you, ſaith the Lord:</hi> whoſe bleſſed Son hath alſo ſaid: <hi>Mat. 5. Bleſſed are the pure in heart: for they ſhall ſee God.</hi> God is to be ſeen by the pure in heart,
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:31335:88"/> ſaith our Saviour; He is to be ſeen dwelling in them, whom he conſecrates for a holy Temple to himſelf; as it is written. <hi>Iſa. 57. For thus ſaith the high and lofty one that inhabiteth eternity, whoſe name is holy, I dwell in the high and holy place; with him alſo that is of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite and humble ſpirit, to revive the ſpirit of the humble, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive the heart of the contrite ones.</hi> Pſal. 147. <hi>He healeth the broken in heart and bindeth up then wounds.</hi> This contrition of heart, ſo acceptable unto God, and ſo much commended in Scripture, doth not dwell nor abide with the anxious deſire of worldly things, and of the pomp and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the age, which are hateful to the Lord. Nor let any Man perſwade himſelf that he can ſerve two Maſters, that is, that he can
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:31335:88"/> pleaſe God, and at the ſame time fulfil the luſts of the fleſh, purſue the vanities, pride and ambition of the World, and obey the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of carnal wiſdom: The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle St. <hi>James</hi> declares it to be impoſſible. <hi>Jam. 4. Ye adulterers and Adultereſſes, know ye not that the friendſhip of the World is enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with God? whoſoever therefore will be a friend of the World, is the enemy of God. Do ye think that the Scripture ſaith in vain, the ſpirit that dwelleth in us luſteth to envy?</hi> And therefore we are earneſtly warned by the Apoſtle St. <hi>John,</hi> that being deluded by vain arguments, or any idle and groundleſs hope and opinion, we ſhould not retain the love of this World, but wholly reject it, if we would approve our ſelves to God, whom we ought to love:
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:31335:89"/> for our own ſalvation. <hi>John 2. Love not the World, neither the things that are in the World. If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Man love the World, the love of the Father is not in him, for all that is in the world, the luſt of the fleſh, and the luſt of the eyes, and the pride of life, is not of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but is of the world. And the world paſſeth away and the luſts thereof: but he that doeth the will of God abideth for ever.</hi> From all which divine ſentences we may conclude, that they who have not carefully avoided the corruption and pollution of life and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and have not laboured to ſhun thoſe things, that are to be ſhunned, will, with all their actions, works and oblations be diſpleaſing and ſo enemies to the pure and holy ſpirit of God. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine wiſdom it ſelf aſſerts this, and
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:31335:89"/> therefore adviſes us not to loſe the fruit of our good works, through our own fault and negligence. <hi>Prov. 15. The Sacrifice of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed is an abomination unto the Lord;</hi> Eccleſ. 34. <hi>He that ſacrificeth a thing wrongfully gotten, his Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is ridiculous; and the gifts of unjuſt Men are not accepted. The moſt high is not pleaſed with the Offerings of the wicked; neither is be pacified for ſin, by the multitude of ſacrifices.</hi> The Prophet expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulates the ſame thing, with thoſe who by their perverſe actions and deeds, both publick and private, polluted the ſacrifices which they frequented. <hi>Bring no more vain oblations, incenſe is an abomination unto me, the new Moons and Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths, the calling of Aſſemblies I cannot away with, it is iniquity, even the ſolemn meeting. Your new
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:31335:90"/> Moons, and your appointed Feaſts my ſoul hateth: they are a trouble unto me, I am weary to bear them. And when ye ſpread forth your hands, I will hide mine eyes from you: yea, when ye make many prayers, I will not hear: your hands are full of blood. Waſh ye, make you clean, put away the evil of your doings from before mine eyes, ceaſe to do evil, learn to do well, ſeek Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, relieve the oppreſſed, judge the Fatherleſs, plead for the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow. Come now and let us reaſon together, ſaith the Lord; tho your ſins be as Scarlet, they ſhall be as white as Snow; tho they be red like crimſon, they ſhall be as wooll. If ye be willing and obedient, ye ſhall eat the good of the Land: but if ye refuſe and rebell, ye ſhall be devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the Sword: for the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it.</hi> This
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:31335:90"/> divine expoſtulation is made up both of promiſes and threatenings to thoſe who either doe, or will not obey: wherefore by the ſame ſpirit the author of this expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, we are invited and ſtirred up, by ſtrong and often repeated reaſons, to ſeek to God for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and the accompliſhment of his promiſes. <hi>Iſay. 55. Let the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forſake his way, and the unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Man his thoughts: and let him return unto the Lord, and he will have mercy upon him, and to our God, for he will abundantly pardon.</hi> Seeing therefore it hath been made out unto us by many clear and manifeſt teſtimonies and Texts of both the Old and New Teſtament, that theſe three heads, to wit, the <hi>fear of the Lord, Repentance</hi> and <hi>brotherly Charity,</hi> as the pure fountains and ſour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:31335:91"/> of all pious actions accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with Faith, are moſt accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to God, and through his gracious favour very inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, not only to make us eſcape the wrath and indignation of God, but alſo find grace and mercy in time of need; and are ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to ſalvation, that without them we cannot pleaſe God, nor obtain the accompliſhment of his promiſes concerning our immortal ſtate and the celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al inheritance purchaſed to us by the death and reſurrection of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. And ſeeing by the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace all Believers are aſſured, that through the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent ſtudy and practice of theſe three points, every one may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their ſhare of that Promiſe and Obligation, which God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:31335:91"/> hath graciouſly and freely propoſed to us for our ſalvation; I thought it my duty, being mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with Chriſtian zeal, and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Charity, to admoniſh and exhort all my fellow Chriſtians, not only by what we have hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to alledged, but by all the ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, ſentences, precepts, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions and exhortations ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by the holy ſpirit, and laid up in the Treaſury of ſacred Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, that they would carefully ſet about the duties of Piety, and diligently proſecute the ſame, in the conſtant practice of theſe three principal Points, the Fear of the Lord, Repentance and Charity. <hi>For no Man putting his hand to the Plough and looking back, is fit for the Kingdom of God; but he that endureth to the end, the ſame ſhall be ſaved.</hi> Now that theſe things
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:31335:92"/> may be religiouſly and rightly performed, we muſt put off all the carnal affections and luſts that war againſt the Soul; theſe, I ſay, which reſiſt divine grace, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tard and keep back the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of that love, whereby <hi>Joh. 3. God ſo loved the World, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whoſoever believeth in him, ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life.</hi> 2 Tim. 2. <hi>If a Man therefore purge himſelf from theſe, he ſhall be a veſſel unto honour, ſanctified and meet for the Maſters uſe, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared unto every good work:</hi> And being enriched with the bleſſings of divine Grace, he ſhall even in this life being, to taſt and ſee that the Lord is good to thoſe that love and fear him. That we may therefore briefly ſumm up all that hath been ſaid of this rule of
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:31335:92"/> Chriſtian Piety, which hath been confirmed by the word of God, delivered in the oracles of the Prophets, and aſſerted in the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of the Apoſtles, and all Holy Writ; we affirm that theſe three heads of Religion are not only of principal uſe, but even abſolutely neceſſary to all ranks and conditions of Chriſtians, for obtaining the ſalvation of their ſouls, and the inheritance and poſſeſſion of the Kingdom of Heaven; and that this is a rule common to all Men, who would live according to the Doctrine, Precepts, and Inſtructions of our Lord. Now theſe Heads, which we have often mentioned, are the <hi>Fear of the Lord, Repentance</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> or Brotherly love; which all of us who profeſs the Doctrine of the Chriſtian Religion, muſt
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:31335:93"/> not only know, but alſo careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practiſe, through the aſſiſtance of the divine grace, which, as we have already ſhew'd, will be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to none that rightly ſeek it; as our Lord and Maſter himſelf does plainly aſſure us: <hi>Luke 11. I ſay unto you, ask, and it ſhall be given you: ſeek, and ye ſhall find: knock, and it ſhall be opened unto you. For every one that asketh, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth: and he that ſeeketh, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: and to him that knocketh it ſhall be opened. If a Son ſhall ask bread of any of you that is a Father, will he give him a ſtone? or if he ask a Fiſh, will he for a Fiſh give him a Serpent? or if he ſhall ask an Egg, will he offer him a Scorpion? if ye then, being evil, know how to give good gifts to your children: how much more ſhall your Heavenly Father give the holy ſpirit to them that ask him?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="179" facs="tcp:31335:93"/>
               <p>We alſo teſtifie, and from the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">The Uſe and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of this Rule.</note> and obſervation of the holy Scriptures, do affirm and declare, that the corruption, depravation and malignity of life and manners, which is to be found amongſt Men of all condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, proceed from the neglect of theſe three Parts of Chriſtian diſcipline, which are as certain firſt Principles of practical Piety, known to all Men who are in their right ſenſes. And the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of theſe three Principles, to wit, of the <hi>Fear of the Lord, Repentance</hi> and <hi>Brotherly-love,</hi> is manifeſt not only to all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, by the light and revealed will of God preached unto them, but alſo to the unlearned and thoſe who know not the written Law, by the ſimilitude and image
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:31335:94"/> of the Deity ſtamped on their minds: tho, as we have ſaid, they be not proved and confirmed to them by ſo many ſentences and oracles of holy Scripture: which, perhaps, is their own fault, ſeeing they mind nothing leſs than the ſerious learning of thoſe things which make for their own ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and whilſt they heedleſly and negligently run over theſe, diligently ſtudy to know and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe the contrary. But though they have not at all learn'd, or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect to be taught the Law, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. Yet <hi>they are a Law to themſelves; which ſhew the work of the Law written in their hearts, their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience alſo bearing witneſs, and their thoughts the mean while accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, or elſe excuſing one another.</hi> Now if theſe three heads of a Chriſtian life, were well known
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:31335:94"/> and carefully practiſed by all, we ſhould experience another kind of efficacy of the grace of God in us, find another chearfulneſs of mind, and other evidences of Faith alſo. Other proofs of our Religion would appear both in publick and private, nor would there ſo many deteſtable inſtances of vice and impiety ſo openly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, in City and in Country, in Courts and private Families, and in all the ſocieties of Chriſtians, where monſtrous and flagitious wickedneſs doth but two much and two often reign; and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Laws are deſpiſed and viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by bloody contentions, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, hatred, ſtrife, calumnies, fraud, deceit, bitter and frequent quarrels, robberies, thefts, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torſions, and defrauding of the poor, beſides the innumerable
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:31335:95"/> arts of violence and oppreſſion, whoredom and uncleanneſs, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, fornication, inceſt, and many other heinous abominations not to be named. So many places of the Chriſtian World would not abound in ſurfeiting and drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, chambering and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs, ſinful and ſenſual de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and pleaſures, and corrupt luxury; nor would there be ſo much vanity and oſtentation, ſo immoderate and uſeleſs expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiveneſs, ſo great emulation and pride, nor ſo vaſt a number of other ſins, and monſtrous wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and impieties, as to woful ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience we daily ſee. But on the contrary, if the fear of the Lord, accompanied with Repentance and Charity dwelt in the hearts of all Chriſtians, the actions of their lives would be ordered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right.
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:31335:95"/> It would then be the chiefeſt care of every one firſt to ſtand in a we and fear, leſt they fall into the hands of the living God: and next that they may obtain forgiveneſs and mercy from him; and ſo every one would endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to perform what they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed in the holy Sacrament of Baptiſm, having entred into Covenant, before a mortal Man, indeed, yet with the immortal God, the Juſt Judg of all the World, the Lord of Hoſts, and the avenger of all ſin and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs; <hi>Pſal. 5. Who is a God that hath not pleaſure in wickedneſs, neither ſhall evil dwell with him. The fooliſh ſhall not ſtand in his ſight; he hateth all workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. He ſhall deſtroy them that ſpeak leaſing: the Lord will abhor the bloody and deceitful Man:</hi> The
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:31335:96"/> ſumm of which promiſe was, To renounce the devil and all his works, the pomps and vanities of this wicked World, and to lead his life according to the Laws of him whoſe Son he would be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted; and every one being endowed with divine fear, inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the deſire of amending his life by Repentance, and inflamed with Brotherly love and Charity; would direct all his works and actions to the advancement, not only of private and particular, but alſo of common and publick Peace, Faith, Juſtice, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Mercy, Honeſty, and, in a word, of the general virtue and ſanctity of all Men: and careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perform the duties incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent upon him, that he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his reward from him who cannot lie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="185" facs="tcp:31335:96"/>
               <head>Of the ſeveral Duties and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of all ranks and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of Men, to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined according to this Rule.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Second Part.</head>
               <p>NOW if theſe three heads of <hi>pure Religion and undefiled before God the Father,</hi> were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by all Men, we ſhould ſee many lively inſtances and effects of that practice; whereof the ſumm is, <hi>James 1. To viſit the
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:31335:97"/> Fatherleſs and Widows, and to keep himſelf unſpotted from the World;</hi> And from theſe fountains of all humane actions, that is the Fear of the Lord, the ſtudy of Repentance, and exerciſe of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, the offices and duties of all degrees, ranks and conditions of Men, might eaſily be drawn and deduced: ſo that the whole body of the Chriſtian Common-wealth, from the crown of the head to the ſole of the foot, would be more healthful and ſound, than at preſent we ſee, and would in all its Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers worthily perform its ſeveral functions: There would be no trouble nor diſcord amongſt the various degrees of Men; but all would conſpire for the mutual good and profit one of another: For the variety of degrees, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:31335:97"/> Miniſteries and Offices, is not to be condemned, but rather ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of and commended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt a Chriſtian People, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing found to be of great uſe and advantage, when they are inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted and executed according to the Laws and Precepts of God. for as St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us; 1 <hi>Cor. 11. The body is not one Member, but many. If the foot ſhall ſay, becauſe I am not the hand, I am not of the body; is it therefore not of the body? and if the ear ſhall ſay, becauſe I am not the eye, I am not of the body; is it therefore not of the body? if the whole body were an eye, where were the hearing? if the whole were hearing, where were the ſmelling? But now hath God ſit the Members, every one of them in the body, as it hath pleaſed him.</hi> And a little after he ſubjoyns:
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:31335:98"/> 
                  <hi>That there ſhould be no Schiſm in the body; but that the Members ſhould have the ſame care one for another<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And whether one Member ſuffer, all the Members ſuffer with it: or one Member be honoured, all the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers rejoyce with it. Now ye are the Body of Chriſt, and Members in particular.</hi> When the ſeveral Members are once perſwaded of this, and in the fear of the Lord; in the ſtudy of Repentance and practice of Brotherly love and Charity, they know their Duties and Offices, there is no doubt but that they will religiouſly ſet about the performance of the ſame. That we may then begin with the firſt and chief or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders<note place="margin">The Duty of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, Rulers and Governors.</note> of the Chriſtian ſtate, it is manifeſt, that it is the duty of Rulers and Governours, and of thoſe who are
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:31335:98"/> to guide and direct others, to take care to maintain the honour of God, and to provide what is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary as well for the ſalvation of the ſouls, as for the honeſt and lawful concerns of the bodies of Chriſtian People, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and diligently to diſcharge their part of the Office and Care, that they have ſeverally taken upon them: not to give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves over to ſloth and idleneſs, to luxury, delights and pleaſures: but by day and by night, though with hunger and thirſt, colds and heats, loſſes and croſſes, perils and dangers both of life and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; to behave themſelves as becomes good, faithful and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Miniſters and Servants, and as that honeſt Keeper of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Mans Cattel, affirmed of himſelf in relation to the Flocks
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:31335:99"/> committed to his care. <hi>Gen. 30. This twenty years have I been with thee; thy ewes and thy ſhe-goats have not caſt their young, and the rams of thy flock have I not eaten. That which was torn of Beaſts, I brought not unto thee, I bare the loſs of it; of my hand didſt thou require it, whether ſtoln by day, or ſtoln by night. Thus I was, in the day the drought conſumed me, and the froſt by night; and my ſleep departed from mine eyes.</hi> And as that excellent ſhepherd did, whoſe task was neither more eaſie nor leſs dangerous, as he himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timates. 1 <hi>Sam. 17. Thy Servant kept his Fathers Sheep, and there came a Lion, and a Bear, and took a Lamb out of the Flock: and I went out after him, and ſmote him, and delivered it out of his mouth: and when he aroſe againſt me, I
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:31335:99"/> caught him by his beard, and ſmote him and ſlew him.</hi> Since theſe holy Shepherds, then, ſhewed ſo much care and diligence, ſo much faithfulneſs and aſſiduity, for ſheep, goats, and brute beaſts, that their owners might ſuffer no loſs, what care then, behoveth it them to take, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78. who <hi>feed</hi> Jacob <hi>the People of the Lord, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>his Inheritance? that they may feed them according to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iegrity of their heart: and guide them by the ſkilfulneſs of their hands:</hi> whom they know to be the Flocks not of an earthly and mortal, but of an eternal and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Lord and Maſter, 1 <hi>Pet. 1. Not redeem'd with corruptible things is Silver and Gold; but with the precious blood of Chriſt, as of a Lamb without blemiſh and without ſpot.</hi> Now they muſt be led out and
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:31335:100"/> fed not in ſtrange Paſtures, but in the Meadows and Fields of the Lord; as it was the care of Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned the ſame to the Paſtors, who lawfully diſcharge that duty, not once or twice, but a third time, ſaying: <hi>John 21. Simon Son of Jonas, loveſt thou me more than theſe?</hi> to which when he had anſwered, <hi>yea Lord, thou knoweſt that I love thee: he ſaith unto him, feed my Lambs.</hi> He ſaith unto him again, <hi>Simon Son of Jonas loveſt thou me?</hi> and he anſwering; <hi>yea Lord, thou knoweſt that I love thee,</hi> he ſaith unto him, <hi>feed my Sheep.</hi> And he ſaid unto him a third time, <hi>Simon Son of Jonas, loveſt thou me?</hi> and when he had an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the third time: <hi>Lord thou knoweſt all things, thou knoweſt that I love thee:</hi> he ſaith unto him:
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:31335:100"/> 
                  <hi>feed my Sheep:</hi> This care which Jeſus Chriſt ſo earneſtly and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionately commended to Paſtors, the Ancients Religiouſly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took, and gloried in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance and diſcharge of the ſame; as particularly St. <hi>Paul: 2 Cor. 11. In labours more abundant, in ſtripes above meaſure, in priſons more frequent, in deaths oft, of the Jews five times received I forty ſtripes ſave one. Thrice was I beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en with rods, once was I ſtoned, thrice I ſuffered Ship-wreck; a night and a day I have been in the deep: In Journeying often, in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils of waters, in perils of Robbers, in perils by mine own country-men, in perils by the heathen, in perils in the city, in perils in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in perils in the ſea, in perils among falſe brethren; in wearineſs and painfulneſs, in watchings often,
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:31335:101"/> in hunger and thirſt, in faſtings often, in cold and nakedneſs. Beſides thoſe things that are without, that which cometh upon me daily, the care of all the Churches. Who is weak, and I am not weak? who is offended, and I burn not?</hi> The Apoſtle was not only ſatisfied that he had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered theſe things for the ſake of the ſouls committed to his charge, but alſo, as we have already ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, gloried and greatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced that by undergoing ſuch troubles and care he might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove himſelf unto God; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſubjoyned, 2 <hi>Cor. 12. Therefore I take pleaſure in infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, in Reproaches; in Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, in Perſecutions, in Diſtreſſes for Chriſts ſake.</hi> Of the like mind were the other holy Miniſters of the Goſpel alſo, <hi>Acts 5. who departed from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:31335:101"/> of the Council, rejoycing that they were counted worthy to ſuffer ſhame for his name. And daily in the Temple, and in every houſe, they ceaſed not to teach and preach Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Such endeavours, and ſuch inſtances of duty and faithful obedience God always expects of his Paſtors and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and when they are need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful requires them. Now when are they not needful? what time is there, that affords not occaſion and opportunity for a ſtrenuous diſcharge of the Miniſtry? what reaſon, colour or pretext can be given for idleneſs, and neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Sheep? what if there be no dangers, but all things in peace and quietneſs? yet oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities and ſeaſons of doing thoſe things which concern the ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Souls are never wanting:
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:31335:102"/> there is always occaſion for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing and encreaſing the favour and love of God, and for avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch a complaint and reproof as this. <hi>Ezek. 34. Wo be to the Shepherds of Iſrael that do feed themſelves: ſhould not the Shepherds feed the Flocks? ye eat the fat, and ye cloath you with the wooll, ye kill them that are fed: but ye feed not the Flock. The diſeaſed have ye not ſtrengthned, neither have ye healed that which was ſick, neither have ye bound up that which was broken, neither have ye brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain that which was driven away, neither have ye ſought that which was loſt: but with force and with cruelty have ye ruled them. And they were ſcattered, becauſe there is no Shepherd; and they became meat to all the beaſts of the field, when they were ſcattered? My Sheep
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:31335:102"/> wandred through all the Mountains, and upon every high hill: yea, my Flock was ſcattered upon all the face of the Earth, and none did ſearch or ſeek after them. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ye Shepherds hear the word of the Lord; as I live ſaith the Lord God, ſurely becauſe my Flock became a prey, and my Flock be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came meat to every beaſt of the field, becauſe there was no Shepherd, neither did my Shepherds ſearch for my Flock, but the Shepherds fed themſelves and not my Flock: Therefore, O ye Shepherds, hear the word of the Lord; Thus ſaith the Lord God, behold I am againſt the Shepherds, and I will require my Flock at their hand, &amp;c.</hi> Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to theſe complaints and dreadful threatnings of the Lord God, are the rebukes given by our Saviour to the Lazy, Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious,
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:31335:103"/> Covetous and negligent Miniſters and Paſtors of his Flock. <hi>Luke 11. Wo unto you, ye Lawyers: for ye lade Men with burdens grievous to be born, and ye your ſelves touch not the burden with one of your fingers. Wo unto you Scribes, Phariſees, Hypocrites; for ye are like unto whited Sepulchres, which indeed appear beautiful outward, but are within full of dead Mens bones, and of all uncleanneſs.</hi> Thoſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and Miniſters who dread ſuch reproofs and threatnings of the Holy Ghoſt, will forſake o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther affairs which concern not, but rather obſtruct their function, and with all diligence and pains, will ſet about the diſcharge of that duty which has been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them from above: Nor will they think it enough to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:31335:103"/> others with the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Churches, who ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly mind their profit, but ſlightly their duty, or others, by whom Children are only taught to ſay a few Prayers by heart, whilſt by age they are unable to do or underſtand any thing elſe: Nay, rather, themſelves being neither tired out by labour, fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by dangers, nor diſcouraged by difficulties, will never leave off to watch over, viſit, and take account of the Flock of God, and to take care of, and inſtruct Chriſtians of all ages, ranks, and conditions in the neceſſary duties of true and ſolid Piety. This, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, is a heavy charge, and not to be performed without much labour and pain; but it is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe moſt acceptable to the Lord and Maſter of the Flock, who
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:31335:104"/> laid down his life for his ſheep: and will never withdraw the help and aſſiſtance which he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, to thoſe who ſtudy to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge aright the office of their Miniſtry. <hi>And loe,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>I am with you to the end of the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now it behoves every one, with a Religious awe and fear to take heed and look to himſelf, that by Ambition, Avarice, Bribes, Intereſt or other arts he aſpire not to that noble Miniſtery, nor be found ſo doing by that Juſt Judg from whom the ſecrets of the heart and actions of Men are not hidden, and who allows no Man for his own ends, by his own arts and induſtry, and without a-lawful Call and Election, to canvaſs for, or ſtep into that holy function, nor to undertake the duties of
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:31335:104"/> the ſame, unleſs he be endowed with thoſe virtues and qualities; which are ſet down and expreſly deſcribed by the Holy Ghoſt: for, <hi>Tit. 1. A Biſhop muſt be blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, as the Steward of God; not ſelf-will'd, not ſoon angry, not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to wine, no ſtriker, nor given to filthy lucre; but a lover of hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, a lover of good Men, ſober, juſt, holy, temperate; holding faſt the faithful word, as he hath been taught, that he may be able by ſound doctrine, both to exhort and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the gainſayers.</hi> Happy is that Flock that has a Paſtor ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed and qualified, then would there be fewer diſeaſes, leſs ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful idleneſs and fewer ſcabs and putrifying ſores to be ſeen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Sheep; ſo much error, ignorance, deluſion and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion would not be found amongſt them. In a word,</p>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="202" facs="tcp:31335:105"/>
                  <l>Non inſueta graves tentabunt pabula foetas,</l>
                  <l>Nec mala vicini pecoris conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia laedent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No novell food their teeming Flocks would cloy,</l>
                  <l>Nor no contagious neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ills annoy.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>But on the contrary, at what time the ſovereign Lord, ſhould come to viſit the Flock which he hath committed to the care of good Shepherds; he would find it pure and clean, free from all impious and falſe doctrines, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out errors, nurtured and bred up in ſound Diſcipline and ſolid In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, healthy and plump, comely and beautiful, as being fed with the ſound food of pure
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:31335:105"/> and heavenly Doctrine: which will not only be moſt acceptable to their Lord and Maſter, but will alſo procure to the Paſtors a moſt certain and excellent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. And what, and how great that may be hoped to be, the chief of the Apoſtles St. <hi>Peter,</hi> declares to his fellow-labourers in the Goſpel. 1 <hi>Pet. 5. The El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders which are among you I exhort, who am alſo an Elder, and a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Sufferings of Chriſt, and alſo a partaker of the glory that ſhall be revealed: feed the Flock of God, which is among you, taking the overſight thereof, not by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, but wilfully; not for filthy lucre, but of a ready mind; neither as being Lords over Gods heritage, but being enſamples to the Flock: and when the chief Shepherd ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, ye ſhall receive a crown of glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y that fadeth not away.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="204" facs="tcp:31335:106"/>
               <p>And we make no<note place="margin">The Duty of inferiour Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</note> doubt but that if the three Heads which have been already pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, be carefully obſerved in the lives and manners of inferiour Miniſters, Prieſts and Deacons, and all that ſerve at the Altar; it will be a moſt profitable and ſure way to procure the grace and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of God, not only to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but to all thoſe alſo, who war under their conduct in the Church of Chriſt: for where the fear of the Lord, the ſtudy of Repentance and the fervent vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of brotherly love and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity dwell abundantly; there, neither Pride nor Ambition, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Hatred nor Injuſtice, neither Backbiting, Vanity, Pomp nor Oſtentation, nor any of thoſe vices, which are wont to war a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:31335:106"/> the foul, and the honeſty and integrity of life, have any place: but rather Honeſty. Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, Juſtice, Peace, Concord, Mildneſs, Mercifulneſs, Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, Civility, Gravity, and all the other Virtues which accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny theſe, and ſpring from thoſe three Heads, as from pure Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of Chriſtian Piety, will be eminent and conſpicuous. Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours will Rule, Govern and Correct their Inferiours, with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal love and affection. Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours will ſubmit unto, obey and love their ſuperiours, as the Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerents and Vicars of Jeſus Chriſt our Redeemer, the Lord, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and Head of his Church. And both will retain in their minds, and practiſe in their lives, what is enjoyned by our Saviour. <hi>Luke 22. The Kings of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:31335:107"/> exerciſe Lordſhip over them; and they that exerciſe authority up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, are called benefactors. But ye ſhall not be ſo: but he that is greateſt among you, let him be as the younger; and he that is chief, as he that doth ſerve.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now in all that we have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſaid, or ſhall hereafter ſay, it is not our intention to obſerve what the practice of all and every one is, but only to admoniſh and declare what they ought to do, as we premiſed in the beginning of this Treatiſe. For it hath always been our deſign and conſtant pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, not to give offence to any Man living, but only to propoſe to all what Chriſt our Supreme Lord and heavenly Maſter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of us and of all that would be his Diſciples and Followers.</p>
               <pb n="207" facs="tcp:31335:107"/>
               <p>And therefore, that we may proſecute the Offices of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ranks and qualities of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, ar we have propoſed in the beginning; how uſeful and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous the three chief Heads of our Chriſtian Rule, to wit, the <hi>Fear of the Lord, Repentance</hi> and <hi>Brotherly Love,</hi> are to Kings, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces<note place="margin">The Duties of Kings, Princes and Magiſtrates.</note> and Magiſtrates, for ordering and carrying on their affairs with Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, Wiſdom, Dexterity and Succeſs, and thereby for the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of their own Salvation; the very Offices and Charges which they bear, do declare. For ſuch Miniſters are appointed by God; not that they ſhould only conſult their own intereſts, and indulge and pleaſe their own hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, but that they ſhould with
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:31335:108"/> all care and induſtry provide for the people of God thoſe things that are known to conduce to the promoting of true Chriſtian Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, publick honeſty, peace and tranquillity, innocence and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs, according to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and directions of the divine wiſdom. Now they who endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and ſtudy to do ſo, muſt ſhew themſelves to be Princes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: not ſlaves to pride, ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſtrife, hatred, deceit, frauds and avarice; not approving, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring, or admitting any thing that is not good, juſt and honeſt; not imitating crafty arts, the ſly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of diſſimulation and humane cunning: nor out of private re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, or for fulfilling their own luſts, or ambitious deſires, being the authors of the devaſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, plundrings and ruine of
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:31335:108"/> Countrys, Cities, Towns and Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages: nor vexing and oppreſſing poor Chriſtian People with heavy and inſupportable Taxes and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions: but propoſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as patterns and examples to other Men, of publick equity innocence and righteouſneſs; and making their lives and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions a rule to private Men, of continence, modeſty and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; reckoning themſelves, no leſs than other Chriſtians, bound and obliged by that Covenant which they entered into in their Baptiſm, and diligently obſerving that neceſſary renunciation which they then made of the Devil and all his works. If theſe things were rightly obſerved, one Prince would not invade the Kingdoms, Cities, Towns and Rights of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſtians, nor detain what
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:31335:109"/> he had unjuſtly uſurped. By this means, mutual Charity and Peace would keep, not only Princes themſelves, but alſo their Vaſſals and Subjects in their duty; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty would commend, and Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and Authority adorn them; Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice would reign amongſt Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; the zeal of Gods honour every where appear, in exact obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the precepts and holy commandments of God: and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in common and united deſires, purpoſes, words and works, that promiſe would be fulfilled, which was made by all Chriſtians, none excepted, in Baptiſm. For if the true nature of Regal, Imperial, and Princely Authority be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, it will manifeſtly appear; that theſe high and ſupreme dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, have for that end been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by God, that they who
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:31335:109"/> are honoured with them, ſhould be the Guardians, aſſerters and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengers of the holy Laws of God, be, and have the title of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of their People; that they ſhould rightly adminiſter Juſtice, puniſh the guilty and tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the Law, put to death o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and incorrigible Malefactors, protect the poor and weak from the violence and oppreſſion of the powerful and rich, defend the innocent againſt the attempts of the wicked, and maintain the fatherleſs and widows: In a word, that they ſhould endeavour what in them lyes, to keep and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve all the Members of the State, both high and low, great and ſmall, rich and poor, in peace, concord, tranquillity and ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. This, I ſay, is the true end, for which the dignity and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:31335:110"/> of Kings, Princes and chief Magiſtrates is appointed by God, from whence it follows, that needleſs Pomp and oſtentation with voluptuous greatneſs, the affectation of Arbitrary domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the deſigns of boundleſs am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, and the conſequents thereof the dangers and loſſes of ſouls, bodies and eſtates, and the exceſſive haraſſing and overchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Subjects, are both diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to God, and grievous to the people.</p>
               <p>Nor is it only the Office of Kings and Princes, to cauſe the reſt of Mankind to be inſtructed and kept in the duties of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Piety, Honeſty, and in the fear of God, and to ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the Miniſters of the Will of God and Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline, but it is their proper duty alſo as
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:31335:110"/> they are Princes, To know the Law of God, carefully attend to, and diligently practiſe and obey the ſame, being led by the fear of the Lord, in all the actions of their lives and adminiſtrations of their Government. As it is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned by this ſingular Precept: <hi>Deut. 17. It ſhall be when the King ſitteth upon the Throne of his Kingdom, that he ſhall write him a copy of this Law in a Book, out of that which is before the Prieſts and the Levites. And it ſhall be with him, and he ſhall read therein all the days of his life: that he may learn to fear the Lord his God, to keep all the words of this Law and theſe Statutes, to do them: that his heart be not lifted up above his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and that he turn not aſide from the commandment to the right hand or to the left: neither ſhall he
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:31335:111"/> multiply Wives to himſelf, that his heart turn not away: neither ſhall he greatly multiply to himſelf Silver and Gold;</hi> leſt truſting therein, he fall into avarice and covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which the Apoſtle calls Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, and the root of all evil. They are not to reſpect perſons in Judgment, nor to take bribes; <hi>Eccleſ. 20. For Preſents and Gifts blind the eyes of the Wiſe,</hi> and make them liable to that dreadful Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence pronounced againſt thoſe that pervert Judgment: <hi>Deut. 27. Curſed be he that perverteth the Judgment of the Stranger, Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and Widow.</hi> Of which exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable practice, theſe Judges and Magiſtrates are taxed, of whom it is written: 1 <hi>Sam. 8. They turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed aſide after lucre, and took bribes, and perverted Judgment.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="215" facs="tcp:31335:111"/>
               <p>But ſeeing it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that ſo many Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces,<note place="margin">The Duty of inferiour Magiſtrates</note> Cities and Towns as may happen to be in one Chriſtian Kingdom, can be Governed by the pains and care of the Prince alone; divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence has appointed that Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Magiſtrates and other publick Miniſters ſhould be conſtituted, who may carefully and dutifully diſcharge the Offices and Truſt that is repoſed upon them. <hi>Deut. 16. As it is written, Judges and Officers ſhalt thou make thee in all thy Gates which the Lord thy God giveth thee throughout all thy Tribes: and they ſhall Judge the People with juſt Judgment. Thou ſhalt not wreſt Judgment, thou ſhalt not reſpect perſons, neither take a gift: for a gift doth blind the eyes of the Wiſe, and pervert the
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:31335:112"/> words of the Righteous. That which is altogether Juſt ſhalt thou follow.</hi> And in another place. <hi>Exod. 18. Provide out of all the People, able Men, ſuch as fear God, Men of Truth, hating Covetouſneſs; and place ſuch over them, to be Rulers of Thouſands, and Rulers of Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, Rulers of Fifties, and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of Tens. And let them Judge the People at all Seaſons, &amp;c.</hi> Which kind of Men when <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaphat</hi> had choſen, he thus admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed them: 2 <hi>Chron. 19. Take heed what ye do: for ye Judge not for Man, but for the Lord, who is with you in Judgment. Wherefore, now, let the fear of the Lord be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, take heed and do it: for there is no iniquity with the Lord our God, nor reſpect of Perſons, nor taking of Gifts. Thus ſhall ye do in the fear of the Lord, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:31335:112"/> and with a perfect heart.</hi> And that this courſe was followed by Princes and Magiſtrates who were approved of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Holy Hiſtory aſſures us.</p>
               <p>Now ſo much holier ought Chriſtian Princes and Magiſtrates to be, ſo much more verſed in the ſtudy and knowledge of Law and Equity, by how much they have obtained a more perfect Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament than the Ancients did, not only becauſe of the clear and plain expoſition of the divine Precepts made by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, but alſo becauſe of more abundant grace promiſed and prepared for Believers under the Goſpel. It is very far from their duty then, either by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion or omiſſion to break the Law, and violate the ſacred Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts; and that they who are
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:31335:113"/> commanded always to read and meditate on the Law, and not to turn aſide from the right, neither to the right hand nor to the left; ſhould mind nothing but plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, pomp, ambition and ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, and go aſtray after their own inventions, making and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Laws upon others, which make more for the appetites and deſires, the greatneſs, State, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and Glory, (as they are pleaſed to call it) of the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors; and for eſtabliſhing many new titles of Authority, Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative and Superiority, which they daily invent, than for the true Worſhip of God, and good of the People. Beſides, it is a ſort of perverſeneſs moſt odious to God, for Princes, or inferiour Magiſtrates, to covet to be rich, and to leave great Eſtates to their
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:31335:113"/> Children, out of the publick Revenues: and not being ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with an honeſt reward for their labours, that is, with a modeſt competency of ſubſiſtence, according to their quality, to be inſatiably ſet upon the getting of wealth and riches, either by the liberality of Princes, or defraud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Publick, and to make it the whole deſire of their Souls, that they may raiſe great Houſes and Families, whereby they may perpetuate their Names upon Earth, rather by a long Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Heirs, than by the Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Examples of Virtue, Innocence, Sanctity and real Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Samuel</hi> born in <hi>Ramah,</hi> a little Town, and in a Montainous Country, being from his child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood brought up in the ſacred
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:31335:114"/> Miniſteries of the Temple, had a garment given him yearly by his Parents, ſuitable to the meanneſs of their Fortune. When he was grown up to be a Man, by the command of God he took upon him the Government of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, and during the ſpace of fourty years, as Prince, Judg, and Ruler, in Peace and in War, Ruled the populous, rich, and flouriſhing State of the whole twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> being as painful and aſſiduous, as vigilant and active as any Governor, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before or ſince; and yet du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that whole time, he neither encreaſed his Eſtate, nor changed his abode from his own mean na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive habitation, to a more conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous City, at leaſt in his own Tribe; nor for his pleaſure made uſe of the delights and varieties
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:31335:114"/> that other places did afford: but having in War recovered and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhed the State of the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, and ſetled a firm Peace all over the Country, he kept Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies at certain times for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtring Juſtice to the People, and when he had done ſo, that he might not be troubleſom or chargeable to any Town or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, he returned home to his own mean, but contentful habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, where he neither excuſed himſelf from buſineſs, nor omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted any opportunity of promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the worſhip of God. As it is written, 1 <hi>Sam. 7. And the hand of the Lord was againſt the Philiſtines, all the days of</hi> Samuel. <hi>And the Cities which the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines had taken from Iſrael were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to Iſrael, from</hi> Ekron <hi>even unto</hi> Gath, <hi>and the Coaſts thereof
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:31335:115"/> did Iſrael deliver out of the hands of the Philiſtins: And there was Peace between Iſrael and the Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites. And</hi> Samuel <hi>Judged Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael all the days of his life. And he went from year to year in Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit to</hi> Bethel, <hi>and</hi> Gilgal, <hi>and</hi> Mizpeh, <hi>and Judged Iſrael in all thoſe places. And his return was to</hi> Ramah; <hi>for there was his houſe: and there he Judged Iſrael, and there he built an Altar unto the Lord.</hi> By the ſhort deſcription of this inſtance, the Holy Ghoſt manifeſtly ſhews us, with how much care, diligence, innocence, piety, continence and abſtinence, that great Man diſcharged the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of a valiant and expert Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral in War, and of an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Prince and Magiſtrate in Peace, who, when afterward he had dimitted the Government, and
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:31335:115"/> reſigned up the Authority to a choſen King, was neither richer nor more wealthy, nor was his Family advanced to greater dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity or ſplendor; but he conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly returned to the ſame ſtat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wherein he was born. For <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> went to <hi>Ramah,</hi> where he ſpent the reſt of his days; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did he build Palaces or ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Houſes, either in <hi>Ramah,</hi> or in any other more conſpicuous place, nor erected for himſelf a magnificent Monument or bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing place, on which, either at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> or any other City ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in War, he might tranſmit to Poſterity the Trophies of his At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievements, or the Titles of his Fame. 1 <hi>Sam. 25. But</hi> Samuel <hi>died, and all the Iſraelites were-ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together and lamented him, and buried him in his houſe at</hi> Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mah.</p>
               <pb n="224" facs="tcp:31335:116"/>
               <p>For they who aim to be rich by their Magiſtracy, muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity either cheat the King, or defraud the Publick; and apply that to their own private uſe which might far better and more profitably be expended on the Publick: Now the publick trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure being exhauſted, the people muſt needs be haraſſed with new Taxes and Impoſitions; and ſo the Wealth and Riches of a few, muſt cauſe the want and poverty of many. But how much God is offended at theſe covetous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, the Prophet plainly declares, <hi>Iſa. 5. Wo unto them that joyn houſe to houſe, that lay field to field, till there be no place, that they may be placed alone in the midſt of the earth. In mine ears, ſaid the Lord of Hoſts, of a truth many houſes ſhall be deſolate, even great and
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:31335:116"/> fair, without Inhabitant.</hi> Now if it be unbeſeeming a Chriſtian Magiſtrate to heap up riches from the Salaries or larger Perquiſits of their Offices; how deteſtable and accurſed muſt it be in the ſight of God, to get Eſtates and Dignities, by accepting of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Injuſtice, Rapine, Fraud, Bribes, Oppreſſion, Calumny and Cheating? God forbids Kings, Princes, and Magiſtrates, to mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply to themſelves Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: for the greedy thirſt after Gold and Riches, ſets the minds of thoſe who are infected there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, upon the committing of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sin and Wickedneſs: it is the cauſe of the Oppreſſion of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with grievous and heavy Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, of Quarrels, Strife and Wars amongſt Princes themſelves, of the ſlaughter and murdering
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:31335:117"/> of Subjects, and other abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and flagitious cruelties, that are committed by Soldiers; and, in a word, of the ruine and loſs of many Souls, as the Holy Ghoſt himſelf aſſures us: <hi>Jam. 4. From whence come Wars and Fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings among you? Come they not hence, even of your Luſts that War in your Members? ye luſt and have not: ye kill, and deſire to have, and cannot obtain: ye fight and war, and ye have not, becauſe ye ask not: ye ask, and receive not, becauſe ye ask amiſs, that ye may conſume it upon your Luſts.</hi> And whilſt matters go thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe who profeſs the Faith, and pretend to Piety and Religion: the Chriſtian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth and true Piety are leſſened and impaired; the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous and wicked Empires and
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:31335:117"/> Kingdoms of Chriſts enemies, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and are enlarged, Hereſies and erroneous and accurſed Sects, ſpring up and daily grow greater and greater. God ſet before us an illuſtrious and noble pattern of Chaſtity and Continence, in the perſons of his own Princes: ſaying, He ſhall not multiply to himſelf many Wives, that may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure his mind. That was not lawful to the ancient Kings of the people of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> and ſhall it therefore be lawful to Chriſtian Princes, to deflower Virgins, rob Women of their Honour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and by their foul ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample tempt others to the deſire or act of the ſame filthineſs, till they know no more the number of them they have debauched and wronged? Kings and Princes who would approve themſelves
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:31335:118"/> to God, are forbidden in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture to lift up their hearts in Pride above their brethren. It would be horrid wickedneſs then, to uſe Tyranny, Inhumanity, Pride, Ambition, Haughtineſs, Arrogance, Inſolency and Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty towards Chriſtian Subjects; and ſo to treat them, as if they were Heathen Slaves bought with their Money, for the ſatisfaction of their Luſts and Pleaſures, their Luxury, Vanity and Pride. God forbids any Man to aſpire to Power and Supremacy, to arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate it to himſelf or any way to invade it; he will not have any Man to be the Lord and Maſter of his People, except thoſe who are appointed by his Favour and Authority, or are declared to be ſuch by the juſt Right of Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance. And therefore we dare be
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:31335:118"/> bold to affirm, that it is not Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for any Man that profeſſes himſelf to be a Diſciple of Chriſt, and fears the Judgment of God, either by Favour, Intereſt or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Faction, or by Force, Fraud or Deceit, by Money, Gifts or Promiſes, to invade the Rights and Places of others, or to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them being unjuſtly invaded. It is a barbarous and inhumane thing to do ſo, altogether repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Chriſtian Doctrine, and only to be practiſed by Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh Tyrants, and perverſe Infidels, who are therefore liable to the ſevere and grievous puniſhments of a terrible Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Now ſeeing it is the command of God that the Miniſters and Officers of Kings and Princes, ſhould be choſen from among the
<pb n="330" facs="tcp:31335:119"/> beſt and fitteſt of the People, who are far from Covetouſneſs and Ambition. It would be a bad cuſtom amongſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, to appoint thoſe for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Eccleſiaſtical or Civil employments, who endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſcrew themſelves into Place by Bribes or Largeſſes, Arrogance or Oſtentatiom, or other ſuch arts and politick ſlights; and it would be worſt of all, if unworthy and unfit Perſons, vitious, covetous and ambitious Men, ſhould be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to Magiſtracy, either by the ſole favour of Princes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any conſideration of merit, or for a reward of other ignoble ſervices, or upon the account of Money, ſolicitation of friends, recommendation of Ladies, or other worldly by-reſpects. But if
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:31335:119"/> Princes and Magiſtrates being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with the three above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Heads of Chriſtian Piety, will carefully and diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet about the performance of the duties of their ſeveral places and employments, they will omit no occaſion of executing Juſtice and Judgment with all integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and they will give no place, either in City or Country, in publick or in private, to the ſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, diſobedient, licentious, fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and corrupt humors of wicked and perverſe Men: The fruit whereof will be, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and pleaſures, luxury and uncleanneſs, pride and violence, brutiſhneſs and ſenſuality, and, in a word, the contempt and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of the Laws of God, reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and abounding no more in Chriſtian Countrys, Cities and
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:31335:120"/> Towns; they will not be like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe Cities, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaies, were for unrighteouſneſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered up to a Reprobate ſenſe; or be by God, Judged worſe than <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> nor be liable to that character, which the Prophet put upon thoſe who neglected Righteouſneſs and Judgment. <hi>Jer. 9. They be all Adulterous, an Aſſembly of treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Men. And they bend their tongues like their bow for lies: but they are not valiant for the Truth upon the Earth; for they proceed from evil to evil, and they know not me, ſaith the Lord. Take ye heed every one of his neighbour, and truſt ye not in any brother, for every brother will utterly ſupplant, and every neighbour will walk with ſtanders. And they will deceive every one his neighbour, and will
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:31335:120"/> not ſpeak the truth; they have taught their tongue to ſpeak lies, and weary themſelves to commit iniquity. Jer. 6. For from the leaſt of them even unto the greateſt of them, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one is given to covetouſneſs; and from the Prophet, even unto the Prieſt, every one dealeth falſly.</hi> All theſe things happen where the fear of the Lord, true Piety and Juſtice are neglected by Princes and Magiſtrates: which is the cauſe that Thefts, Robberies, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Adulteries, whoredom, Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, Perjury, Uſury, Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to Parents, Irreverence towards Superiours; in a word, the forgetting and contempt of the commandments of God, and all other horrid vices and impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, are ſo frequent, and that beſides the eternal deſtruction to which they hurry Men headlong,
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:31335:121"/> they make Chriſt, and the moſt pure and holy Chriſtian Religion, not only to be deſpiſed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, but alſo reproached and evil ſpoken of by barbarous and unbelieving Nations, and perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Jews; when they ſee and obſerve Chriſtian Countrys and Cities full of Murderers, Uſurers, Deceivers, Cheats, Backbiters, Robbers, Thieves, Bauds, Whores, Adulterers, and other flagitious Sinners; abounding in Hatred, Envy, Suſpicions, Injuries and Offences; void of Peace, Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity and Honeſty: and laſtly, practiſing Carnal Licentiouſneſs, and all the tricks and artifices of Fraud and Cunning. All which vices and wickedneſſes are ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed from thence, where the decency of an honeſt Chriſtian Converſation, and the Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:31335:121"/> and love of Gods Commands are encouraged by Princes and Magiſtrates, where Injuries, Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies, Revenge and Contentions, are not reckoned Honourable, but Diſgraceful to Perſons and Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies; where Virtue only is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded; but Cruelty and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, Immodeſty, Inhumanity, Pride and Arrogance are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenanced and hiſſed at. Now it is impoſſible that in thoſe places where Rulers and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors do their duty, and give good example to others, Murderers, Thieves, Robbers, Blaſphemers, Adulterers, perjured Perſons, Panders, Uſurers, Cheats, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous and hurtful perſons, Witches, Wizzards, Sorcerers, or any deſpiſers and tranſgreſſors of the Laws of Heaven ſhould harbour and abide, but that all,
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:31335:122"/> according to the direction of God, ſhould, as much as may be, be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely rooted out, not only leſt by their crimes and wickedneſs they may hurt others, but leſt they ſhould by their filthy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation corrupting the whole Body of the State, and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the tender Youth, allure them into the like Crimes, and render their Scholars worſe than the Maſters: becauſe we are all apt to learn and imitate wicked and bad examples; for as the divine Oracle ſaith, <hi>Gen. 8. The ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination of Mans heart is evil from his Youth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor would any reaſon of State allow, if the fear of the Lord, Repentance and Brotherly-love, dwelt as they ought, in the hearts of Princes, that open Malefactors, diſturbers of the publick Peace,
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:31335:122"/> and thoſe that hurt and corrupt the Innocent and Simple, who by the Authority of divine Law are utterly to be expelled and caſt out of Chriſtian Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſhould either be ſuffered to live in their own Country, or be received, protected and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by other Princes; or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured by Paſs-ports and ſafe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts; leſt thereby they might be continued alive to the ruine and deſtruction, either of the Princes and Magiſtrates from whom they have fled, or of thoſe by whom they are received. If this were punctually obſerved, we ſhould find greater reverence paid to the Law, leſs licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and wanton and raſh Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs amongſt Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>For neither is divine Juſtice divided; nor is any wicked, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure,
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:31335:123"/> or incorrigible perſon, tho tranſported to any place of the Earth, approved of, or accepted of God, nor ought good and godly Princes ever to admit ſuch to any place in their favour or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs. for it is written: <hi>Pſal. 5. For thou art not a God that hath pleaſure in wickedneſs, neither ſhall evil dwell with thee. The fooliſh ſhall not ſtand in thy ſight: thou hateſt all workers of iniquity. Thou ſhalt deſtroy them that ſpeak leaſing: the Lord will abher the bloody and deceitful Man.</hi> Now that this Judgment and Counſel of God ought to be followed by thoſe Princes, who ſtudy and endeavour to approve themſelves to the Lord and Prince of Princes, that holy profeſſion of the Prince ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Gods own heart, plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demonſtrates. <hi>Pſal. 101. I
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:31335:123"/> will walk within my houſe with a perfect heart. I will ſet no wicked thing before mine eyes: I hate the work of them that turn aſide, it ſhall not cleave to me. A froward heart ſhall depart from me: I will not know a wicked perſon. Whoſo privily ſlandereth his neighbour, him will I cut off: him that hath a high look, and a proud heart, will not I ſuffer. Mine eyes ſhall be upon the faithful of the Land, that they may dwell with me: he that walketh in a perfect way, he ſhall ſerve me. He that worketh deceit, ſhall not dwell within my houſe: he that telleth lies, ſhall not tarry in my ſight. I will early deſtroy all the wicked of the Land: that I may cut off all wicked doers from the City of the Lord.</hi> The authority of divine Juſtice is perpetual and unalterable; which ought equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:31335:124"/> to be regarded by all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Princes, nor muſt they think it is divided, or to be executed by halves, but they muſt obſerve it wholly and entirely, ſquaring it by the Will and Precept of the King of Kings, and Lord of all the Earth: who when he had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Cities of Refuge or San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuaries amongſt his People, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they who had killed any one without malice or inveterate and confirmed hatred, might fly to eſcape revenge; concerning o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who with a deliberate pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of mind committed the fact, he thus Enacts. <hi>Deut. 19. If any Man hate his neighbour, and lie in wait for him, and riſe up againſt him, and ſmite him mortally that he dies, and fleeth into one of theſe Cities: then the Elders of his City ſhall ſend and fetch him thence,
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:31335:124"/> and deliver him into the hand of the avenger of blood, that he may die: thine eye ſhall not pity him, but thou ſhalt put away the guilt of innocent blood from Iſrael, that it may go well with thee.</hi> The ſame Juſtice he commands to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. 19, 22, 24. againſt Thieves, Robbers, Cheats, Raviſhers, Adulterers, and other open Offenders, and publick violators of Juſtice, Truth and Honeſty, all whom he will have taken out of the way, that the evil may be put away from Iſrael; and therefore to the ſeveral ſentences he adds: <hi>And ſo ſhalt thou put away the evil from among you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſince the Chriſtian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine hath taught the reſt of the Officers of Kingdoms and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths,
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:31335:125"/> all Judges, Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, Advocates, Proctors, Clerks, and other ſubſervient Miniſters of Magiſtrates and Courts of Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the fear of the Lord, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and Brotherly-love; it will not allow them to Practiſe or get Eſtates by Fraud, Deceit, Cavilling, Petty-fogging, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious interpretation of the Law, protracting of Suits, ſtarting of litigious Proceſſes, ſuperfluous invention of Pleas, or by falſe information againſt the Innocent, or unjuſt defence of the Guilty. For this Doctrine condemns all haughtineſs of mind, Luxury, Pride, and Ambition, and all vices that are fed and cheriſhed by riches even innocently got; but much more ſeverely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns Men who get Eſtates and live ſplendidly of the ſweat and
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:31335:125"/> blood of their Chriſtian Brethren, and by their Fraud, Craft, cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and over-reaching, and ſuch ways as exceed; the perverſeneſs of which God ſadly complaining, thus threatens by the Prophet, <hi>Jer. 5. Among my People are found wicked Men: they lay wait as he that ſetteth ſnares, they ſet a trap, they catch Men. As a Cage is full of Birds, ſo are their Houſes full of Deceit: therefore they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come great, and waxen rich. They are waxen fat, they ſhine: yea, they over paſs the deeds of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: they Judge not the Cauſe, the Cauſe of the Fatherleſs, yet they proſper: and the right of the needy do they not Judge. Shall I not viſit for theſe things? ſaith the Lord: Shall not my ſoul be aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on ſuch a Nation as this?</hi> from ſuch crimes muſt all the Officers
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:31335:126"/> of a State flee, who in proſpect of Salvation, endeavour to live Godly, Juſtly, and Honeſtly in this preſent wicked world; and they ought to make it their whole care and buſineſs, that Equity, Juſtice and Moderation may flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, both in publick and private; and that the powerful, rich and crafty, may not unjuſtly impoſe upon the weak, poor and ſimple, ſince that charge is ſeriouſly preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon them by God himſelf. <hi>Iſa. 1. Learn to do well, ſeek Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, relieve the oppreſſed, Judge the fatherleſs, plead for the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now as to the Rich, and ſuch as<note place="margin">The Duty of the Rich.</note> endeavour to be ſo; if they would remember their promiſe made in holy Baptiſm, and confirmed by covenant with
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:31335:126"/> the Lord, if they reſolve to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after, and practiſe holineſs according to the rules of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Piety, they may eaſily and plainly learn from the Doctrine of our Lord and Maſter, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the three aforementioned Heads, how far otherwiſe they ought to behave themſelves, both in getting and ſpending of Eſtates, than moſt part of Rich Men uſually do. For the Unjuſt, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous and Inſatiable Deſire of Riches, and the vain, ſuperfluous, ambitious, or ſelfiſh uſe of them, are not conſiſtent with the fear of the Lord, the duty of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and Brotherly-love of Chriſtians, which approve not thoſe advantages that wealth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes to pleaſures and luxury; but rather condemn them; The Chriſtian Doctrine that adviſes
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:31335:127"/> thoſe who would be ſaved, not to truſt to Riches, commending Honeſty, Modeſty, Temperance, Innocence, Continence, Mercy, Bounty, Liberality, and the other Duties of Piety and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; and on the contrary deteſting and diſſwading from the oppoſite vices, as Pride and Haughtineſs, Delights and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, Injuries, Robberies and Oppreſſion of the Poor, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining or Cheating the Labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers Wages, Uſury, Monopolies, enhaunſing of prices, and every thing elſe, that is either diſgrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the doer, hurtful to our Chriſtian Brethren, or inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with the publick good, in the Judgment of God himſelf. For he who reckons all Chriſtians his Brethren, and Children of one Common Father, the Juſt,
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:31335:127"/> Merciful and Bountiful God, and ſhall know that they ſtand in need of his help, ought to aſſiſt them partly by giving, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by lending without any hope of profit, benefit or intereſt; and thereby magnifie God the Father, who hath enabled him to ſhew that kindneſs to his Brethren, which the liberal goodneſs of God hath promiſed to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe with a ſure and excellent reward. For ſo it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>Luke 6. Do good and lend, hoping for nothing again: and your reward ſhall be great, and ye ſhall be the children of the higheſt: for he is kind to the unthankful and to the evil. Be ye therefore Merciful, as your Father alſo is Merciful.</hi> To this duty of beneficence enjoyned by Chriſt to his Diſciples, we may add that
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:31335:128"/> ſtrict command of God. <hi>Deut. 15. If there be among you a poor Man of one of thy brethren, within any of thy Gates, in thy Land which the Lord thy God giveth thee, thou ſhalt not harden thy heart, nor ſhut thine hand from thy poor brother: But thou ſhalt open thine hand wide unto him, and ſhalt ſurely lend him ſufficient for his need, in that which he wanteth. Beware that there be not a thought in thy wicked heart, ſaying, the ſeventh year, the year of releaſe is at hand: and thine eye be evil againſt thy poor brother, and thou giveſt him nought, and he cry unto the Lord againſt thee, and it be ſin unto thee. Thou ſhalt ſurely give him, and thine heart ſhall not be grieved when thou giveſt unto him: becauſe that for that thing the Lord thy God ſhall bleſs thee in all thy works, and
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:31335:128"/> in all that thou putteſt thine hand unto. For the poor ſhall never ceaſe out of the Land: therefore I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand thee, ſaying, Thou ſhalt open thine hand wide unto thy brother, to thy poor, and to thy needy, in the Land.</hi> The ſincere Diſciples of Chriſt ought to ſet before their eyes, and think on that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God, that is backed with ſo many reaſons, commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſo many promiſes, and arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſo many threatnings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the neglecters of it, and freely beſtow and lend according to their abilities; avoiding what in them lies, that ſentence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by the Holy Ghoſt, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the rich Men of this World, and not in good works. <hi>Jam. 5. Go to now ye rich Men, weep and houl for your miſeries that ſhall come upon you. Your riches are cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted,
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:31335:129"/> and your Garments are Moth-eaten, your Gold and Silver is Cankered; and the ruſt of them ſhall be a witneſs againſt you, and ſhall eat your fleſh as it were fire: ye have heaped treaſure together for the laſt days. Behold the hire of the Labourers, which have reaped dawn your Fields, which is of you kept back by Fraud, erieth: and the cries of them which have reaped are entred into the ears of the Lord of Sabaoth. Ye have lived in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure on the Earth, and been wanton; ye have nouriſhed your hearts, as in a day of ſlaughter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſonant to this ſentence is that dreadful commination of Chriſt: <hi>Luke 6. Wo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you that are rich: for ye have received your conſolation. Wo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you that are full, for ye ſhall hunger: wo unto you that laugh
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:31335:129"/> now: for ye ſhall mourn and weep.</hi> And is it not a very terrible ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence that is pronounced, and with an aſſeveration confirmed by our Saviour againſt rich Men? <hi>Mat. 19. Verily I ſay unto you, that a rich Man ſhall hardly enter into the Kingdom of Heaven. And again I ſay unto you, it is eaſier for a Camel to go through the eye of a needle, than for a rich Man to enter into the Kingdom of God.</hi> The reaſon of this difficulty the Holy Ghoſt affirms to be, becauſe the deſire and love of riches deceives Men, and turns them often out of the ſtreight road of Equity and Juſtice. For he that deſires to be rich, haſtens to be ſo: but then what reſpect is there to the Law? what fear or ſhame in him who ſets his ſoul upon wealth? nay plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and opulency when once it is
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:31335:130"/> acquired, debauches both Men and Women from an innocent, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt and honeſt way of living, into luxury, vanity and pomp, into pride and ſtrife, and into o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther violations of the divine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and contempt of Chriſtian ſimplicity, ſetting off enormous vices with great and plauſible names; ſo prone is the ſinful appetite of Man to abuſe even the advantages and bleſſings of earthly things; a fault careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be avoided, as the Apoſtle admoniſheth: 1 <hi>Tim. 6. But they that will be rich, fall into temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and a ſnare, and into ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fooliſh and hurtful luſts, which drown Men in deſtruction and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: for the love of money is the root of all evil: which while ſome coveted after, they have erred from the faith, and pierced themſelves
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:31335:130"/> through with many ſorrows.</hi> And therefore, that good Men may be ware of that deceitfulneſs of riches, <hi>Pſal. 62. The holy Ghoſt by the mouth of the Prophet,</hi> gives this admonition. <hi>If riches encreaſe; ſet not your heart upon them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor is the holy Doctrine of our Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter<note place="margin">The duty of Merchants and Tradeſmen.</note> more remiſs or obſcure in informing all thoſe who live, and endeavour to get Eſtates by Traffick and Trades. For ſuch are taught by the fear of the Lord, the ſtudy of Repentance, and Brotherly Love, to deceive no Man; not to adulterate or change; dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh or increaſe their goods and commodities, nor to neglect any thing that relates to them, which the nature of the goods require; not to change and raiſe their
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:31335:131"/> prices, nor to deal fraudulently in weights and meaſures: for the holy Scriptures aſſure us, that all ſuch frauds and cheats argue a contempt of divine Juſtice, Chriſtian ſimplicity and upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and are extremely offenſive to the ſupreme Judge of all Men. <hi>Prov. 11. A falſe ballance is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination to the Lord: but a juſt weight is his delight.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>Prov. 20. Divers weights and divers meaſures, both of them are alike abomination to the Lord.</hi> Nor is that cuſtom of cheating and circumventing our brethren, by falſe prices and oaths, and a cunning wheadle of words, leſs abominable to God; as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. <hi>Amos 8. Hear this, O ye that ſwallow up the needy, even to make the poor of the Land to fail, ſaying, when will the new Moon be
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:31335:131"/> gone, that we may ſell corn? and the Sabbath, that we may ſet forth wheat, making the Ephah ſmall, and the Shekel great, and falſifying the ballances by deceit? That we may buy the poor for Silver, and the needy for a pair of Shooes; yea and ſell the refuſe of the wheat? The Lord hath ſworn by the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of</hi> Jacob, <hi>ſurely I will never forget any of their works. Shall not the Land tremble for this, and every one mourn that dwelleth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in?</hi> whoſoever are the true diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and followers of Chriſt will fear and ſtand in awe to offend God, and to be liable to ſuch threatnings: whatever art or profeſſion they follow, they'l ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage the ſame with all faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and care, and behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves modeſtly and juſtly in the buſineſs they ſet about, neither
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:31335:132"/> wronging their brethren in their work, nor exacting too much for their labour, nor overvaluing the goods they ſell them; but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing to themſelves charity and the good of others, rather than covetouſneſs, and abominating all filthy and forbid gain, they will be content with the lawful gettings of their callings, and ſhun and deſpiſe the pride of life, as a thing altogether inconſiſtent with the ſimplicity of their vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
               <p>But that we may now deſcend from the publick ſociety and duties of Mankind, to the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular relations of private perſons, and enter into the houſes and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of Chriſtians; we are to take notice, what the mutual du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of private perſons in a family are; and how they are to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:31335:132"/> by Chriſtians, as in the preſence of God, who is a Judge and witneſs of all their actions.</p>
               <p>Chriſtian Women and Wives who deſire to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their lives according<note place="margin">The duty of Women and Wives.</note> to this ſhort but univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal rule of Chriſtian Piety, muſt ſtudiouſly avoid all Pride, Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance, Vain-glorious Boaſting, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, Haughtineſs, Back-biting, and evil ſpeaking; ſhewing nothing in their converſation, of Volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſneſs, Wantonneſs, Luſtful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Idleneſs, or Curioſity, and giving no example of Anger, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, Diſcord, Grudge nor Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice: Put on the contrary, they are in all things to approve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Modeſt, Peaceable, lovers of Truth, Charity and Simplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Dutiful and Obedient to their Husbands and Yokefellows,
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:31335:133"/> in all things that are lawful and honeſt. For theſe ornaments and certain proofs of true virtue, are always conſpicuous in thoſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Women, who fear the Lord, practiſe Repentance, and live ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily in Brotherly-love and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity with all Men: To which they are alſo enjoyned by the holy Precepts of the ſpirit of God, with aſſurances of his favour if they perform, and of his anger and indignation, if they omit and neglect their duty. <hi>Eph. 5. Wives ſubmit your ſelves unto your own Husbands, as unto the Lord. For the Husband is the head of the Wife, even as Chriſt is the head of the Church: and he is the Saviour of the body. Therefore as the Church is ſubject to Chriſt, ſo let the Wives be to their own Husbands in every thing.</hi> Wives who ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:31335:133"/> and heartily ſtudy Piety, will not mind gorgeous attire, rich, coſtly and gaudy apparel, which by decking and ſetting off the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, Eclipſes the beauty, gravity and modeſty of the mind, but ſuch as being prepared by virtue, is an argument of probity and chiefly deſigned to render them acceptable to God and beloved of their own Husbands. For that attire and dreſs is moſt commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable and graceful in a Wife, which adorns the mind, and makes her lovely in the ſight of God, and her own Husband, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable to all others; that being the ornament which the Holy Ghoſt preſcribes and commends, as becoming a Chriſtian Wife. 1 <hi>Pet. 3. While they</hi> (the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands) <hi>behold your chaſt conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation coupled with fear. Whoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorning
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:31335:134"/> let it not be that outward adorning, of plaiting the hair, and of wearing of gold, or of putting on of apparel: but let it be the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Man of the heart, in that which is not corruptible, even the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a meek and quiet ſpirit, which is in the ſight of God of great price. For after this manner in the old time, the holy women alſo who truſted in God adorned themſelves, being in ſubjection unto their own Husbands.</hi> And tho God would not have ſuch to be ignorant or negligent of their own duty; yet he does not approve that they ſhould be tatlers, or diſputers, or that they ſhould arrogate to themſelves wiſdom and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, nor would he have them to be greedy of many teachers, or deſirous of much learning; but being ſatisfied with the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="261" facs="tcp:31335:134"/> of true Piety, and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Candor and Simplicity, that they ſhould buſie themſelves in the exerciſe and practice thereof. 1 <hi>Cor. 14. Let your Women keep ſilence in the Churches: for it is not permitted to them to ſpeak; but they are commanded to be under o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, as alſo ſaith the Law. And if they will learn any thing let them ask their Husbands at home: for it is a ſhame for Women to ſpeak in the Church.</hi> And again in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place. 1 <hi>Tim. 2. Let the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men learn in ſilence with all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection. But I ſuffer not a Woman to teach, nor to uſurp authority over the Man, but to be in ſilence. For</hi> Adam <hi>was firſt formed, then</hi> Eve, <hi>And</hi> Adam <hi>was not deceived, but the Woman being deceived was in the tranſgreſſion. Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhe ſhall be ſaved in Child-bearing,
<pb n="262" facs="tcp:31335:135"/> if they continue in Faith, and Charity, and Holineſs with So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame Doctrine<note place="margin">The duty of Husbands.</note> and Diſcipline of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Piety comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under the three aforemention'd Heads, the <hi>fear of the Lord, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> and <hi>Brotherly-love,</hi> if it be rightly known and practiſed, will alſo keep Men in their duty, and to the performance of the chaſt Vows and Promiſes of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage; for it enjoyns Husbands to love their Wives, and to have the ſame care of them as of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but eſpecially, as the moſt important concern of Marriage, to conſult and provide for the eternal ſalvation of the Wife, not only by frequent and reiterated admonitions, but alſo by good and wholſom examples, and, if
<pb n="263" facs="tcp:31335:135"/> it be needful, by undergoing all kinds of danger, and running the risk of life and fortune for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing that end. The whole of this duty is by the Holy Ghoſt ſumm'd up in this Precept. <hi>Eph. 5. Husbands love your Wives, even as Chriſt alſo loved the Church, and gave himſelf for it: that he might ſanctifie and cleanſe it with the waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of water, by the word, that he might preſent it to himſelf a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Church, not having ſpot or wrinckle, or any ſuch thing; but that it ſhould be holy and without blemiſh. So ought Men to love their Wives, as their own bodies: he that loveth his Wife, loveth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. For no Man ever yet ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his own fleſh, but nouriſheth and cheriſheth it, even as the Lord the Church: for we are Members of his body, of his fleſh, and of his
<pb n="264" facs="tcp:31335:136"/> bones. For this cauſe ſhall a Man leave Father and Mother, and ſhall be joyned unto his Wife, and they two ſhall be one fleſh. This is a great myſtery, but I ſpeak concerning Chriſt and the Church. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs let every one of you in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, ſo love his Wife, even as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and the Wife ſee that ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence her Husband.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now thoſe houſes<note place="margin">Domeſtick Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline.</note> and families are moſt acceptable to God, which are reared upon the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the fear of the Lord, Repentance, and Brotherly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>love, where Children and Servants are both by inſtitution and example inſtructed in the duties of Virtue and true Piety, and taught to diſcharge the ſeveral offices of their ſtations; to fear and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence their Fathers and Maſters,
<pb n="265" facs="tcp:31335:136"/> and to ſubmit to the Authority of the Maſter of the Family, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed and eſtabliſhed by the Laws of God. Wherefore it ought to be the care and ſtudy both of Maſters of Families, and of Children and Servants, That all ſhould diligently diſcharge their ſeveral parts, the one in commanding, the others in obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and all in mutual helping and aſſiſting of one another, in promoting the good of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, the practice of Piety, and the ſalvation of their Souls. For ſo are Families enjoyned by the Holy Ghoſt, to know and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe their duties. <hi>Epheſ. 6. Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, obey your Parents in the Lord: for this is right. Honour thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and thy Mother, (which is the firſt Commandment with Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe) that it may be well with thee,
<pb n="266" facs="tcp:31335:137"/> and thou mayeſt live long on the earth. And ye Fathers, provoke not your Children to wrath: but bring them up in the nurture and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition of the Lord. Servants be obedient to them that are your Maſters according to the fleſh, with fear and trembling, in ſingleneſs of your heart, as unto Chriſt: not with eye-ſervice, as Men-pleaſers, but as the Servants of Chriſt, doing the will of God from the heart; with good will doing ſervice, as to the Lord, and not to Men: knowing that whatſoever good thing any Man doth, the ſame ſhall he receive of the Lord, whether he be bond or free. And ye Maſters, do the ſame things unto them, forbearing threatning: knowing that your Maſter alſo is in Heaven, neither is there reſpect of perſons with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="267" facs="tcp:31335:137"/>
               <p>Nor is it conſiſtent with Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Doctrine and Truth, that Children who ought to be edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated by their Parents in the fear of the Lord, and in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and practice of Piety, ſhould be bred up in the Principles of corrupt and perverſe Doctrine, and led in the broad way that tends to deſtruction, being from their infancy indulged and pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered in Pomp and Pride; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced in Luxury, Worldly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, and Luſtful Pleaſures; taught all the lewd Songs, Sports, and Exerciſes of the Age; and made acquainted with the facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Principles, Feuds and Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities of their Parents, which from their Cradle upward they purſue and promote: ſeeing thereby it happens, that the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Chriſtians who ought to
<pb n="268" facs="tcp:31335:138"/> be holy and imitable examples to all the World, of Religion, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, Reverence and Piety to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, become the ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous patterns of Diſhoneſty, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, Irreverence and Impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety both againſt God and their Parents. Servants and Domeſticks alſo encouraged by the publick and private examples of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, both in ſocieties abroad and families at home, grow, through the neglect of thoſe who ſhould puniſh and correct them, proper inſtruments of Unfaithfulneſs, Diſobedience, Robberies, Thefts, Oppreſſions, and the diſgrace of Families; ſo that all thoſe em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments almoſt which in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are good and lawful, run out of courſe, and degenerate into corrupt Nuyſances. Now it is manifeſt that this perverſeneſs
<pb n="269" facs="tcp:31335:138"/> and depravation of manners always happens, when Chriſtian People are not taught the pure, ſimple, true and ſevere Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Goſpel: or if they be taught it, either through an inveterate habit of ſinning, whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſlight and neglect it, or if they commend and approve it, yet think it not ſo abſolutely neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as that they ought to prefer it before all other things that come in competition therewith, and ſo receive the word that is ſown by the Husband-man, in ſtony or thorny ground. But we ought greatly to fear and have a care that that complaint of the Lord may not ſeem to be uttered againſt us. <hi>Jer. 5. A wonderful and horrible thing is committed in the Land. The Prophets propheſie falſely, and the Prieſts bear rule by
<pb n="270" facs="tcp:31335:139"/> their means, and my People love to have it ſo: and what will ye do in the end thereof?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now to conclude, what ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſoever moved by the fear of the Lord, ſhall ſeriouſly conſider upon the wrath and indignation of God, that he hath deſerved, and the ſevere and terrible Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to which he has made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf liable; and ſhall again medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate in his own thoughts that Grace, Mercy, and the bleſſing of Heaven is ready prepared for him, if he will but carefully and heartily endeavour to be cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Wedding Garment, that is, to follow the rule of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty above deſcribed; unleſs he be more than impious, and given o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to a reprobate ſenſe; there is no doubt but that he will turn with full purpoſe of heart and
<pb n="271" facs="tcp:31335:139"/> ſoul, from Vice to Virtue, from corruption to integrity, from madneſs and folly, to a ſound mind, and, in a word from the ſlavery of the Devil, to that mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful Lord, who is ſo pleaſed with the ſerious and true Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of Sinners, that with an Oath he has ſworn he deſires it, and has freely promiſed his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings to thoſe who hope in his Mercy, and turn to him with their heart. <hi>As I live ſaith the Lord God, I have no pleaſure in the death of the wicked, but that the wicked turn from his way and live.</hi> He that hath ears to hear let him hear, and turn to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, if he deſire to obtain mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy from the moſt High; who healeth the broken in heart, and bindeth up their wounds: by whoſe grace, aſſiſtance, good
<pb n="272" facs="tcp:31335:140"/> will and pleaſure, we have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten this practical Rule of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Piety, for the inſtruction of our fellow-Chriſtians; hoping that the meditation and ſtudy thereof may be uſeful to them for obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſalvation, through the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God; to whom be honour and glory for ever and ever, Amen.</p>
               <p>It hath not been our purpoſe to ſet off this Chriſtian Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with the ornaments and flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes of exquiſite Language and Rhetorick; but rather in few and plain words to accommodate this Doctrine of Piety to the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities of all Chriſtians, who might thereby more eaſily both learn and retain it; it being our deſire rather to deliver and teach uſeful and good ſenſe, than gay and painted words. Now the
<pb n="273" facs="tcp:31335:140"/> ſum of all that hath been ſaid, is ſhortly this. That extraordinary and ſupernatural gifts and graces are promiſed to all Men, who will believe and accept the ſame, not only in this life, but alſo more eſpecially in that which is to come; and the ſame purchaſed and conveyed to them by the virtue and efficacy of that won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful myſtery of the conception, birth, death and reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God; who is ready to beſtow them on every one, who in the fear of the Lord obeys the holy dictates and precepts of the Law, and is dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and ſincere in the practice of Brotherly-love and Charity. For God requires that Men ſhould fear, obey, worſhip and ſerve him, and upon theſe conditions gave us his promiſes; to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance
<pb n="274" facs="tcp:31335:141"/> of which he obliged himſelf out of meer grace and bounty. And this is the duty which every Chriſtian, whether high or low, learned or unlearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ought to know and practiſe.</p>
               <p>But for all other things which Men may deſire to know and learn, relating either to their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate capacities, or to the rank and quality which they bear a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Men, and wherein they may be deceived, miſtaken and err; ſince all Men are not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Judges of ſuch things, we have purpoſely omitted them, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting all and every one, that having diligently conſidered and obſerved the abovementioned three heads, they would keep that ſtation, wherein by right and Law they are placed; not decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the right or to the left
<pb n="275" facs="tcp:31335:141"/> from their common duty, which being faithfully performed, God of his goodneſs, will impart to all, what is neceſſary to be known and practiſed by every one in the place and degree that he is called to in ſociety. Now if any thing appear unſeemly and not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo juſtifiable in the actions and conduct of others; it is not the part of any private Man to Judg and Cenſure it, or to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour any change or alteration in the Duties and Offices of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; but to leave the care of that to the lawful Miniſters, and Magiſtrates, and to pray the Lord of the Vineyard, that he would ſend fit Labourers into his Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, and that he would advance, protect and defend his own Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt. Without doubt, the Lord will have pity on his inheritance,
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:31335:142"/> and take care of the welfare and proſperity of his people; and will highly approve, that no Man for the fault or errour of another, withdraw himſelf from the unity and concord of the eſtabliſhed Church and Government; but that every Man mind, not what other people do, but what be ought to do and perform himſelf, and with heart and ſoul ſet about it.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:31335:142"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
